<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Abhishek Nagekar&#39;s Blog</title>
 <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://www.nagekar.com"/>
 <updated>2017-02-21T19:54:20+05:30</updated>
 <id>https://www.nagekar.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Abhishek Nagekar</name>
   <email>abhishek@nagekar.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Trek To Bramhatal (Uttarakhand)</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2017/02/trip-to-bramhatal-uttarakhand.html"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2017/02/trip-to-bramhatal-uttarakhand</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	Hello! It has been more than a month since I shared something here. Although there has not been much, I&#39;d like to share my experiences of the trip I went on last month. It was one of those trips that I&#39;d remember for a very long time.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Since our first trek in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.in/maps/place/Sandhan+Valley/@19.5128161,73.68568,412m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m5!3m4!1s0x3bdd7710dee4b92b:0x9b038473bf56be32!8m2!3d19.5120912!4d73.686087&quot;&gt;Sayadri ranges&lt;/a&gt; in January 2016, I and my friends had this big wish to go on a Himalayan trek. Finally, in October last year, we decided that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Brahma+Tal/@30.1817437,79.5964069,4816m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m12!1m6!3m5!1s0x39a768e945938639:0x43e521befc21ea5d!2sBrahma+Tal!8m2!3d30.1770418!4d79.589389!3m4!1s0x0:0x43e521befc21ea5d!8m2!3d30.1770377!4d79.5894241&quot;&gt;Bramhatal&lt;/a&gt; would be it. (Not embedding maps because it was too much effort. Also, heavy images ahead. May take some time to load. Patience!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	There were a few reasons for this. Firstly, it was an easy trek. The only real challenge was a bit of high altitude sickness, but it was marginal. Secondly, it was the same group that we went to Sandhan Valley with, so there was this trust factor. Thirdly, it was scheduled for January, hence there was no chance it would coincide with our term tests.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	We started preparing for the trek from November, regularly running 5kms to increase our stamina. We also booked our train tickets, to and fro. Then the long wait began. It was my first trip out with friends and I was really excited. We literally spoke about it every single day in college, all 4 of us. We were scheduled to depart on 21st January to Delhi. The last week was the most difficult. I couldn&#39;t sleep at night, for the thoughts of what was about to come kept me awake. I&#39;m sure Ankit, Manasi and Jyotirmay felt the same. Last two days were reserved for shopping and packing. Not much though, since we were not going to bath for the next 10 days anyway! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Saturday 21st - The journey to Lohajung&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Finally the day came, it was a Saturday. I took my 13kg backpack and left for Thane where all four of us met. We had to leave for Delhi that day. So we left for Hazrat Nizamuddin from Mumbai Central. The journey was a bit hectic, for our seats were separate and the train was crowded with unreserved passengers. But the views outside the train made up for that. Really enjoyed the transition from a comfortable 27 degree Celsius in Mumbai to a chillish 15 something in Delhi. We got down by 7 in the evening, and then by the Metro, we headed for the ISBT bus station, from where we were to board a bus for Kathgodam, Uttarakand. Had some Palak Paneer at the bus stand and boarded the bus. The bus journey was comfortable enough, but the cold wasn&#39;t. By the time we reached Kathgodam at 6 in the morning, the temperature had already dropped below 10. The coldest I had ever experienced. I was shivering like I never did before. Talking was not possible because my facial muscles had just refused to coordinate.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Just 20 meters away from where the bus stopped, we met other guys from our trek. There was a jeep awaiting us, which would take us from Kathgodam to Lohajung (our base village), a little town in the Chamoli district of Uttarakhand, a ten hour drive through the ghats, terrifying and nauseating. Trust me when I say this, it was a very beautiful town. Look just about anywhere and you&#39;d have a wallpaper like scenery, old houses, beautiful people and snow covered peaks in the background. And it was cold. I believe it was 6-7 degrees when we reached there. Walking barefoot on the floor wasn&#39;t possible. The water would numb your hands if you dared to touch it, so washing face was out of question right away. We were welcomed with hot Pakodas and tea. The food there was surprisingly good. Great Dal, Rotis and Sabzi. Rice and a sweet dish at the end. So our trek leader briefed us about the next day. We had to start early in the morning to reach the Bekatal lake by afternoon. We were introduced to the kitchen staff who would carry all the heavy equipments on Donkeys (Kachhars) and make us good food throughout the trek. Also, we had a local guide, Ranjeet dada, who, in spite of being a Redhat Linux certified professional, preferred to be around the mountains rather than Linux boxes. A really cool guy who loved to talk and tell stories. He runs his own ISP in the Van village of Chamoli, and had quite a lot of knowledge about networking and *nix in general. We packed our stuff, and went to bed early.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tuesday 24th - Trek to Bekatal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	We started at 8 am, after having a good breakfast. It was through the town, walking on mud roads to the top. It was not difficult, but exhausting. We continued to walk for some 6 hours that day, taking short breaks every 5-10 minutes, occasionally taking long breaks. We had to ascend some 1000-1500 feet on that day, on a trail of some 5kms. We reached the camp by 2 and were given Rhododendron juice. It was too good, and addictive too. Drank some three glasses of it before I had to stop myself from refilling the fourth time. Then it was lunch and we rested in our tents for a while then. In the evening, we went to explore the Bekatal frozen lake nearby. Seeing a frozen lake is a magical experience. It was just like the one Bear Grylls features on his show &#39;Man vs Wild&#39;. It was awesome!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/bekatal.JPG&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	At night, we lit up a bonfire for some heat and had fun around it, all of us. We were served dinner around it (which we insisted since we didn&#39;t want to go away from fire). The food was great and guess what, they made us dessert at 9,500 feet. It was fruit custard, and it was delicious. We chit chatted around the fire after dinner and at around 10, we were served &#39;hot drinks&#39;. No, it wasn&#39;t alcohol, but Bournvita. It was delicious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wednesday 25th - Trek to Bramhatal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/bramhatal.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/bramhatal2.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	We started early again. Had a good shit (seriously, a challenge in the woods ;P), brushed my teeth and had breakfast. Left for Bramhatal. After an even more exhausting day, we reached Bramhatal. The routine was the same on reaching, juice, lunch, rest, tea and then we set out to explore Bramhatal which was some 15 minutes away from the camp. It was beautiful. The night was similar, with bonfire and good food. The next day was summit day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thursday 26th - Summit day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	It was the Republic Day. We did our morning rituals and gathered near the India Hikes campers. We hoisted the Tricolor, sang the national anthem and took some photographs. We were some 25-30 people together, and it definitely was the most memorable Republic day mornings ever. We then started the walk to the summit. It was at 12,500 feet, and the thinness of air was evident. It was not the longest walk, but definitely the most tiring. We kept walking and at around 12, we reached the summit. It was the top of a mountain, snow covered, surrounded by grasslands on three sides and Himalayan ranges on the fourth. One can see Mt. Trisul (22,000 feet) and Nanda Gunti (19,000 feet) from the summit. It was a clear day and we made full use of it. We hoisted the tricolor again on the summit and took pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/republic_celeb.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The descend took some two hours, and we reached the camp by 3. The rest of the day was just usual stuff and the next day was back to basecamp, Lohajung. It would have not been any more interesting from here, if it wasn&#39;t for the sudden snowfall that started when we were about to go to bed. The temperature dropped to 2 degrees and we were all dancing, when it began to snow. We ran into our tents and slept, assuming we were covered!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/summit.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tricolor on the summit. Nanda Gunti on the left and Trisul on the right!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Friday 27th - Back to Lohajung&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So that night, at around 1.30, the tent broke down. The weight of the snow on top of it was too much for it to handle, and it fell on our faces. The ice cold surface of the tent was touching my forehead and nose, but I only woke up at 5 am. My reflex was to call for help, believing that the tent has got buried under the snow. Thankfully it wasn&#39;t exactly buried, but just broken. We spent the next two hours holding the tent with one hand and trying to sleep. It was terrifying! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Daylight made its way in, and we tried to open the tent to see the situation outside. It was seriously frightening, for the grasslands and plains that we saw a day ago had all vanished and replaced by dead white snow. It was snowing so heavily that it took me an additional 15 minutes to gather courage to move out of the tent to take a dump. That was the most daring shit I had ever taken; a foot of snow, chilly winds and -6 degrees. It was nature at its best and worst, simultaneously.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/snow.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/snow_far.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I spoke to our leader and casually told, &#39;No way we&#39;re going to descend in this weather, right?&#39;. He said we have to, no options. We cannot survive here. My heart sank. He told us to get ready in 30 minutes and we did. Slowly, gathering courage, we started walking in that foot deep snow, following the footsteps of the person in front. Snow was getting collected on our shoulders and bags and it felt great, but also added weight and had to be shaken off. It was probably the bravest thing I had ever done, walking on the slopes with snow hitting my face on one side but maintaining the balance so that I don&#39;t slip and go sliding all the way down a thousand feet. It was for real. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/descend2.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/descend.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	This went on and on for the next 7-8 hours, which were quite easily the toughest 8 hours of my life, slipping and falling multiple times and thinking &lt;i&gt;&#39;I don&#39;t want to die here&#39;&lt;/i&gt; to myself. My shoes, socks and pants were all wet, and my hands had become numb due to the snow. Our faces had turned blue. Finally, we reached the base camp at about 4. I took a bath since I was feeling very, very dirty. It was a bad decision, because after that I was shivering so much that my mouth just lost any coordination that was left. It was all &lt;i&gt;kha-kha-kha-khaana ki-ki-kither ha-ha-hai&lt;/i&gt;. It was fun. I slept for some time then. I woke up to a great non veg dinner, Gulab Jamuns and more Bournvita.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	After dinner, the entire team had a good chat. We were given &#39;High Altitude Trekkers&#39; badge for completing the trek, and ranked amongst ourselves who performed the best on the trek. Then it was story time by Ranjeet dada who shared some of his experiences and the lifestyle of the people in that area. Amazing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Saturday 28th - Back to Kathgodam&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/group.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The next morning, we had some Maggie and black tea, took some group pictures with the staff. They packed out bags on the top of a similar jeep and we set out for Kathgodam. It was better this time, since I enjoyed the scenery and didn&#39;t feel nauseated. Just and hour before reaching, we learned that our train got canceled. We took the public transport buses, and started our journey back to Delhi. We reached Delhi at around 2 in the morning. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sunday 29th - A day in Delhi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Knowing the reputation of Delhi, we decided to spend the night at Hazrat Nizamuddin railway station, so we took a cab from ISBT to Hazrat Nizamuddin and spent some time there, in the waiting room, which was already filled up to the brim. Here we got a chance to freshen up for the upcoming day, so we used it. At around 6 am, we kept our huge backpacks in the cloak rooms, taking the essentials with us, we started our Delhi expedition. We explored a lot of good places that day; Connaught Place, Guru Bangla Sahib, Raj Path, Jan Path, Rapid Metro (Gurgaon), JNU campus (just outside), Hauz Khas village, Chandni Chawk, Red Fort and then back to Hazrat Nizamuddin, in that order. We boarded the Deheradun express that night and reached Mumbai early morning on Tuesday. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bramhatal/jump.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously, what a trip!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>7th Semester And Then</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2017/01/7th-sem-and-then.html"/>
   <updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2017/01/7th-sem-and-then</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;b&gt;Important News!&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Today is probably one of the best days of my life. I got myself a new Internet connection and got rid of that old &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2016/12/BSNL-3g-broadband-rant.html&quot;&gt;BSNL broadband&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	This one is from a private service provider called &#39;Speednet&#39;, and the connection is actually very &lt;i&gt;speedy&lt;/i&gt;. I am getting a latency of &amp;lt;10ms to most of my regularly visited sites (thank you, CDNs) which is nice, because BSNL used to do around 80-100. The transfer rates, which for me are more important than latency alone, hover around 20-25Mb/s which is at least 30 times of what BSNL gave at 3 times of the price, with no connection drops. And of course, no FUP. So finally, my connectivity crises come to an end, at least for now.
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.speedtest.net/result/5950264247&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://speedtest.net/result/5950264247.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Let&#39;s get back to the topic. A very happy new year to all of you. 2016 was a great year. It made us smarter than what we were before, and hopefully 2017 would do the same. I remember updating the status &lt;i&gt;&#39;1/8th engineer already&#39;&lt;/i&gt; sometime three years back. Well today, I&#39;m 7/8th an engineer. If I clear all the subjects, of course.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	This semester was less busy. I think too much work is bad for oneself, because in my case, it made me do nothing. That is the most important thing I&#39;ve learnt this semester. You cannot focus on 3 different things at a time, and expect your brain to switch contexts the moment you switch for Webstorm to Pycharm. Series always works better than Parallel for the mind, and although I had read it before, I got a first hand experience of the line. The takeaway here is, keep in mind there is a fine line between pushing your limits and overburdening yourself, where one brings out the best in you, the other takes away everything. Thanks, Dj.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I have also decided to travel more. The trip to Delhi and Agra made one thing really clear, traveling does make one rich. It adds to the one&#39;s experience store and the benefits are not something you can completely describe in text. It is a feeling. The other thing is meeting new people and talking to them. Different people can give you different perspectives to a thing, and you can use it all the time to challenge your own beliefs. Expressing yourself is great, and the regrets that arise from it are far less troubling than those you get by not doing it. Definitely an important lesson I&#39;ve learnt in 2016.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Also, this pretty girl became part of the family in October. We call her &#39;Zacky&#39; and I&#39;ll write about her in detail in another post. 
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/zacky.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So 2016 was filled with learnings, but of a different kind for nerds such as myself. I think this has come with age plus the amazing people I have around me. I hope you liked this post. As always, thank you for reading. 
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BSNL 3G And Broadband Rant</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/12/BSNL-3g-broadband-rant.html"/>
   <updated>2016-12-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/12/BSNL-3g-broadband-rant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	Aah. Ranting is never fun, but right now I&#39;m so very upset with BSNL &lt;i&gt;[bsnl.in or bsnl.co.in, not sure which one is it that they take seriously, but my guess is neither]&lt;/i&gt; that I&#39;ll do it anyway. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Background: I live in the rural parts of Thane in Maharashtra, and as a result, Internet connectivity is a nightmare. There aren&#39;t many private service providers here, and although wireless is fine, it is too much for me to afford. Plus, there aren&#39;t many providers that have plans in the order of hundreds of gigabytes, so 3G is a no no. Back in 2010, my Dad got us a broadband connection from BSNL. It was a 2Mb/s connection with 1GB of data transfer limit per month. The quality of the connection was crap, and frequent disconnections were part of my life, but having been promoted from the 2G connection that I had before this, it felt okay.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Today, I&#39;m using an expensive 2Mb/s connection with unlimited data cap. The good thing about BSNL, unlike some of the private connection providers, is that it doesn&#39;t disconnect when there is a power outage, which happens all the time here during monsoon, thanks to the phone lines they use which are powered at source and run underground. Unfortunately, that is where the good things (thing, technically. Singular) about BSNL end. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&amp;lt;rant&amp;gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;BSNL Broadband&lt;/b&gt; To start with the broadband criticism, the connection is flaky. How flaky, you might ask. It takes me 2-3 tries before I manage to &#39;successfully&#39; downloading a mere 50MB file, that flaky. That has turned me towards torrents of files as small as 30MB, as then I don&#39;t have to care about the disconnections. Once every month, the Internet connection totally dies, and so does the landline, and the DSL line keeps blinking endlessly, which is when I have to go to their office, register a complaint and the next day they send a &#39;technician&#39; who replaces a few cables, &#39;charges&#39; me a 100 bucks and boom, I am blessed with Internet for 30 more days. For this pathetic service, I pay around Rs. 1400 a month, plus the &#39;technician charges&#39; &lt;i&gt;(or kharcha pani, if you like it desi)&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	And their office. It is a spot on example of a &#39;Government office&#39;. Sluggish staff, who when confronted would act as deaf for the first time, then a nod or if you&#39;re lucky &#39;hmm&#39; the next, at which point any self respecting person would back off and go home angrily, swearing at his own misfortune, but if you manage to gather the courage to ask an elaborate question next, get ready for some random bashing on why it isn&#39;t their job to listen to your problems and why you should have probably never asked the question in the first place. The area around their office feels more hostile than an enemy state. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Have you ever been to a sweet shop and saw the Rasgullas and Gulab Jamuns floating in thick sugary syrup there? That is exactly how these employees look like, wanting to carry on floating in that thick protective fluid of a Government job, forever. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;BSNL 3G&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	It was a few months back that I got so fed up with their broadband services that I decided to go for their 3G services. Immediately you can sense that I&#39;m not a smart guy. I know, right? I bought a dongle worth some Rs. 1600, got a BSNL SIM card and recharged it for the Rs. 1099 unlimited plan. Smart. I would admit, it worked well when it did, but then, that was the problem, it hardly ever did. Call it greed, but I thought, anyway I&#39;m paying a lot on the Broadband, so why not invest the same for a much faster connection. Great plan, or so I thought. It was again, a nightmare. I&#39;ll explain why.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So firstly, the BSNL 3G network had some kind of a personality. It used to disappear randomly, and you would start thinking of all the things you did recently that might have caused it to stall. A 3G dongle with 3G data plan and full network strength, still no data transfer. Why? Then, after having restarted the dongle for 10+ times, resetting it 2 times, trying 5 different places in the house and even the building terrace, and finally driving 8 kilometers to BSNL&#39;s office and trying it under their building to see if it works there, you decide to give up and ask for help.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	And I did. Into their office I sprang. I stood in front of the inquiry counter, but not very surprisingly, I wasn&#39;t asked if I wanted any help. Probably they think people visit their sacred office when they lack entertainment in life. Helplessly, I told the guy that my mobile Internet isn&#39;t connecting in spite of having credit and data balance. Guess what he replied. He said &#39;What office is this?&#39;. I replied, with a bit of a smile on my face now, &#39;BSNL&#39;. He annoyingly corrected, &#39;No. It is BSNL landline and broadband. If you have mobile problems, call the customer care&#39;. Of course, I should have known that. They just sell SIM cards in that large 3 storey building, not support or any of those non trivial tasks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So I went home, with much anger. My work had stopped, my 3 days were wasted, some Rs. 3000 spent on something I would&#39;ve never needed if the broadband had worked well, and now I am completely helpless, I thought. But wait. There is someone who always cares for you when you&#39;re lost, someone who will solve all your technical problems like a friend and follow up to ask if everything was okay. Yes, I&#39;m talking about customer care. So Google&#39;d and I found out their number. Called them up, and they did pick up my call. Yaay. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So I told him my problem, and he confidently replied &#39;Sir, we&#39;re having some problem in our network from the last 2 days. It should be working in a few hours. If not, please call back&#39;. I felt relieved. Not only did this guy knew what was wrong, but he even said &#39;Have a great day thank you for calling BSNL customer care&#39; at the end of the call. Dayam!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So waiting for a few hours, and a few more, and a day more. Finally, since it didn&#39;t work out well, called them up again. This time, same confident tone, the lady said &#39;Sir your device isn&#39;t configured to use our services&#39; and instructed me to re-insert the SIM card, manually configure the access point and call back if I had any problem. Hmm, so this was the issue. Did the job, waited for a few hours, but nothing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Called them up again that evening, a guy picks up. Explained him the problem, and he replied &#39;Sir, your one month Internet pack has expired. Please recharge and it should be working&#39;. Okay, sounds fair, but wait a second. &#39;Hello there, my SIM card is 6 days old. How can a 28 day recharge expire in 5 days?!&#39;. The call drops, probably intentionally.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Called them up again immediately. Somebody picks up. Told them the problem, &#39;Sir we are having a network outage. Please try again in a few hours&#39;. Okay, now I think I can play this game. Just to confirm my doubt, I called them up again within a few minutes, and the reply, unsurprisingly, was to &#39;re-insert the SIM, manually configure the Internet settings and try again&#39;. The best part was they were asking me to call back in case that didn&#39;t solve my problem.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Now that was funny, annoying, shameful and depressing at the same time. I could&#39;ve kept doing it all night, but unlike them, I had some real work to do. It is really an interesting strategy, if you think about it. Explaining the problem takes 3 minutes, and they give the solution in 20 seconds and ask you to call again if that doesn&#39;t solve your problem. Which you will, and after a while, you&#39;re doing it all over again. Great way to get work off your chest, right?  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;BSNL Hungama Scam&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So one day, my dad receives a call. It was from some Hungama.com call center asking his email address. Not knowing what&#39;s going on, and thinking it was from BSNL (at least that is what they told my dad), my dad gave it, and the next month we find 3 new services that &#39;we subscribed to&#39; in our BSNL bill. They were some &#39;Movie on demand&#39;, &#39;Games on demand&#39; and &#39;Movies on demand&#39;, the total for which Rs. 450 were charged and added to the final bill, along with landline and broadband. I was surprised, and so was my Dad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Googled and immediately concluded that a lot of people had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.in/search?q=bsnl+hungama&quot;&gt;fallen prey to this scam&lt;/a&gt;. Got their number, called them up and asked them to drop the services. The guy agreed. Next month, the charges recurred. This was simply unacceptable. But who could you complain to? Service center? No it isn&#39;t their job. Call center? They would cut your call half way through the conversation. Wrote an angry email to their customer care address.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;i&gt;
		Hello,
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
		Please unsubscribe my BSNL telephone number ***-****** from the scam that I was, against my intentions, made to subscribe to. I&#39;m being charged some 444 odd rupees for some crappy services that I, honestly, wouldn&#39;t even care to read the names of. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

		I was earlier told that I&#39;ve been unsubscribed only to find out the charges still recurring. Maybe your incompetent call center folks aren&#39;t that quick with their actions.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

		Waiting for a confirmation from your side. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

		Thank you,
		Abhishek
	&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	And they did unsubscribe me, immediately. Wasn&#39;t that easy? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The BSNL office doesn&#39;t have ADSL modems of their own, but &#39;recommend&#39; buying it from a local store. They also &#39;recommend&#39; calling the same guy in case anyone has any technical difficulties with the Broadband. Turns out, their &#39;technicians&#39; are only good enough for replacing telephone cables.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&amp;lt;/rant&amp;gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So maybe some of you can relate to this. Maybe some of you had similar experience in some other (Government?) sector offices. I really have given up on BSNL. I see them injecting ads into HTML of the pages I visit, ugly banner ads that come up telling me about the amazing unlimited 3G plans they have, unlimited broadband &#39;for as low as Rs. 249 which let&#39;s you download 300GB a month&#39;. They lie pretty well, don&#39;t they. So people reading this, if you have an option, stay away from BSNL. If not, stay strong. And in case anybody from BSNL reads this, man I had so much hopes from &#39;our own Indian&#39; telecom company. I wish you guys were sincere, for there was a time I used to argue with friends on why BSNL was superior, although it wasn&#39;t sincere even then. Hope you enjoyed the post. Feel free to leave a comment below to counter my views or in case you had better or even worse experiences. Thank you for reading.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	By the way, just when I was proof reading the article, this popped up!&lt;br/&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;border:1px solid black;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/rant.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Visit To The Taj Mahal</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/11/a-visit-to-the-taj-mahal.html"/>
   <updated>2016-11-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/11/a-visit-to-the-taj-mahal</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tajmahal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Taj Mahal&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So in the last week of July, 23rd, on a Saturday, I was wondering what should be done tomorrow, Sunday that is. It was going to be my last weekend in Delhi, and I wanted to make it memorable. I had the option to spend the evening with my colleague, but I also had the option to visit Taj Mahal. I had always admired Taj Mahal, I mean, who doesn&#39;t. This was my chance to visit it. It somehow felt like I&#39;ve earned it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	And visiting Taj Mahal was not just important because I really wanted to see it, but because I was scared to go all alone to Agra to see it. I was really scared to go there, and the entire Saturday afternoon I was thinking, Taj Mahal can be visited anytime, let me just spend some time with my colleagues, for they might not be there always. But deep within, I knew that the only reason I didn&#39;t want to go was because I was scared. I was scared of going all alone to Agra, a foreign city which I knew nothing more than the name itself. &lt;i&gt;Let&#39;s see. If I manage to wake up early, I&#39;ll think of going&lt;/i&gt; I said, and slept.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
	Sunday, 24th July, here is a page from my diary.&lt;br&gt;
	&lt;i style=&quot;color: olive&quot;&gt;
		Woke up at 6. Plan was to go to Taj Mahal but knew nothing above it, how to go, where to take train (from). Nothing.&lt;br&gt;
		Thought &#39;let&#39;s go to sleep, will call Sukhpreet and make a plan later. Taj Mahal can be visited anytime.&#39; But something kept telling me this opportunity won&#39;t knock twice, and years later, you&#39;ll remember this decision. Or you won&#39;t.&lt;br&gt;
		Anyway, got ready, (had) bread sandwiches (the cheese ones) and got going. Took metro to Rajiv Chawk and then changed to blue line for Indraprasta. Rickshaw to H. Nizamuddin station and then Mangala express.&lt;br&gt;
		Right now sitting in the sleeper boogie with general ticket with earphones in my ears and writing this piece.&lt;br&gt;
		All of a sudden, I feel so courageous, so different. This day is going to be awesome, I can already feel it.
	&lt;/i&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tajmahal2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
	&lt;i&gt;Awkward selfie.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	By the way, I randomly saw the train standing on the platform ready for departure. I went and sat in a reserved coach with IInd class tickets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	And you can bet it was an awesome day. A great weather in Agra welcomed me, and quickly got along with a great person there. He was the rickshaw driver, whom I paid Rs. 500 for a day&#39;s rent which included &lt;b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Station -&gt; Hotel (for lunch)&lt;br&gt;Hotel -&gt; Taj Mahal&lt;br&gt;Taj Mahal -&gt; Agra Fort&lt;br&gt;Agra Fort -&gt; Shopping center&lt;br&gt;Shopping center -&gt; local Hanuman temple&lt;br&gt;Temple -&gt; another-shopping place&lt;br&gt;Shopping place -&gt; Agra station&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Amazing. Bought a Saree for mom, which was handmade with bamboo threads by the prison workers! Also some &lt;i&gt;petha&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	On my way back, did the same thing. Went and sat in the first train I could spot going towards Delhi; in the reserved compartment; with a second class ticket. But not so lucky this time. The TC fined me with Rs. 300, but also gave me the seat, so I guess it went okay. Reached my flat by around 9:30.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	All in all, a great one day trip. I feel it isn&#39;t necessary to describe Taj Mahal here, but the experience, the people and the difference of cultures was just amazing. That day, I was so proud of myself, can&#39;t describe it here. Closing this essay with a quote I read somewhere and only believed on that day, &lt;i&gt;Working makes you money, but traveling makes you rich&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dropping The Master Plan</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/10/why-no-masters-for-now.html"/>
   <updated>2016-10-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/10/why-no-masters-for-now</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	Back when I was in my first and second year of engineering, I was very optimistic about my future. I liked the idea of starting my own venture, and I really believed that by the end of my graduation, I&#39;ll have something that would sustain me without having to look for a job elsewhere. Believe it or not, I really tried to make that happen. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2014/07/blogging-and-why-it-isnt-for-everyone.html&quot;&gt;Two tech blogs&lt;/a&gt;, numerous startup ideas, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2015/12/bug-bounty-dance.html&quot;&gt;bug bounty dreams&lt;/a&gt; and a lot of side projects, all for various reasons, but a common denominator was to become self sustained.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	But again, that was what I had envisioned. Of course, it didn&#39;t work out as planned. There wasn&#39;t sufficient maturity in me then, and if only everything was that easy, isn&#39;t it? By the first half of third year, I knew things were not going to change. It takes a great deal of talent to create something amazing at such an early stage. I didn&#39;t have it. Suddenly, the belief I had in myself, my hard work and my skills fell apart. I was no longer confident about my future, and I feared failing way too much to be comfortable with that fact. I was vulnerable then.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	To add to the agony, people around me were planning things. They were joining GRE and TOEFL classes to get into a great foreign university. They were doing everything that would get them a certificate, and validate their skills in front of someone; Java, Android and what not. I didn&#39;t have a single certificate for any extra curricular. I remember thinking, &lt;i&gt;How am I going to prove to somebody that I know something about anything. I just can&#39;t.&lt;/i&gt;. The deterioration of thoughts accelerated even further when people started to ask each other what are they doing after graduation. Job? Masters? I thought they were too few options to be given to just about anybody regarding a career path. Why was no one talking about starting something after college, or maybe preparing to work at some dream company, or perusing research in the field of their liking, or working as a freelancer for whatever intrigues them. Am I missing something obvious here?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The &lt;i&gt;What are your plans after college?&lt;/i&gt; questions started hitting me as well. I had to take a decision from the two options that were presented to me. Job or masters. I feared a job, and took masters. M. Tech. from some IIT would look cool, I thought. Started researching about GATE examination, and decided to go for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I told my decision to a few friends, and immediately realized that M. Tech. wasn&#39;t the masters everyone was talking about. At least most of them. This masters is M.S. and it is done by going to the United States and studying there. Masters in India is not cool. It is just like Bachelors, in a specialized field. I don&#39;t have a great opinion about the bachelors study in India, and if masters was going to be like that, I am better off not doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So I decided to go for masters. I knew it was going to be very expensive, but quickly learned finance is available. Okay, so if we stretch a bit, I might get into a college in the US, do my masters, work part time to finance my day-to-day expenses, get into a good company, work for a year or two to repay the loan, and then, life is sorted. A better lifestyle, more exposure to good startups and companies, a good salary and everything I would ever ask for. I would be able to give a better lifestyle to my family, fulfill their dreams and more. Now that&#39;s called a plan. More than anything, it felt safe. Plus all the other smart people are doing it so cannot go wrong with this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	By the end of July, I was totally sure about masters. Abhishek and Dhananjay were going to leave for it soon, and I was thinking about the schedule for my GRE and TOEFL. I had convinced mom and dad, and they even had started to talk about the great things I would see and feel a year from now. I would be the first person from my family to fly abroad for higher education. Or fly abroad. Or fly, for that matter. I really liked that feeling. All sunshine and rainbow. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Later in August this year, I spoke with my mentor about this grand plan of mine. I knew for sure he&#39;d be excited. He was not. He started questioning my decision, and I think he realized that me going to the US was more like the only option I saw, rather than a solid goal in itself. We spoke for sometime, and the more I spoke to him, the more I realized that the other &lt;i&gt;over ambitious&lt;/i&gt; plans of mine were not at all over ambitious. They were just as possible as the other safe options, only I&#39;ll have to work a little harder to get to them. The extraordinary people I look up to and admire are just ordinary people who did something extraordinary. And given that you only get one shot at life, let&#39;s aim for something similar, something full of uncertainties, something that is fun and something that I actually want to be doing! That was all the motivation I needed to pursue my heart. That conversation opened me up to the numerous possible career options I had as an engineer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I created a &lt;i&gt;decision matrix&lt;/i&gt; to evaluate my options and find out the best one for me. It gave me my end goal. Now I was free to peruse it the way I wanted. It definitely saved me a lot of time and money. But most importantly it gave me back what all of us are taught during our childhoods. The &lt;i&gt;you can do anything if you try&lt;/i&gt; spirit. I am glad I took everything I came across with an open mind. I tried my options, and chose what was best for me. Thinking over it again, I think there is risk involved in everything. The safe path was never safe. The current path is full of risks as well. But it is just a matter of what risks I am more comfortable with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Finally, a great learning experience. Now the question I ask myself, will I ever consider a masters, again? I remember talking to Sukhpreet about the same. He&#39;s the guy you want to bet on, who knows how to get work done and deliver. He had told me there&#39;s an inner calling that helps you to take decisions. Masters is one such decision. He never had that calling. He has learned all that he needed while working. I haven&#39;t had that calling yet. If ever I do, then yes, why not. Until then, I&#39;ll be sticking to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2014/07/self-learning-is-it-worth-efforts.html&quot;&gt;self learning&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2010/02/24/self-education-failings/&quot;&gt;deeper version&lt;/a&gt; of it. Let&#39;s see how it goes! Thank you for reading.
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fun With Infrared Motion Sensor</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/09/fun-with-infrared-motion-sensor.html"/>
   <updated>2016-09-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/09/fun-with-infrared-motion-sensor</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	Very few of the projects I&#39;ve done actually had any real life purpose. The rest were just &lt;i&gt;Can I do it?&lt;/i&gt; projects. Here&#39;s one more to that little list. So last year, the fan switch in my room changed its position, from the spot where it was in a one arm distance behind my desktop computer table, to a spot where I had to walk three steps, climb my bed and walk another three steps to reach. Too much effort for something that is required to be done tens of times in a day. Naturally, I didn&#39;t bother to turn it off whenever I left the room, and at times, the fan used to stay running long after I had left, until mom or dad noticed it and turned it off again, just before giving me a nice stare. Something had to be done. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I had this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.in/REES52-PIR-Motion-Sensor/dp/B01HOP1V0Q&quot;&gt;PIR module&lt;/a&gt; that I had bought a couple of years ago with a friend. PIR [for Passive Infrared] sensor triggers when a hot body comes in its range, like a human being. I had to make use of it somehow to control the fan in the room. I had to Google just about everything about this project, and slowly I discovered that you cannot just put the AC mains and DC circuits on the same breadboard, and expect them to be nice to each other. As a result, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.in/Channel-Arduino-Raspberry-Silicon-TechnoLabs/dp/B0181W7QSW&quot;&gt;relay&lt;/a&gt; was discovered. [The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sparkfun.com/products/100&quot;&gt;one I have used&lt;/a&gt; is a more compact, cheaper version].
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So a relay to act as a switch to turn the fan on and off, a PIR sensor to detect me entering the room and something in between to interface the two. &lt;i&gt;Arduino should do it&lt;/i&gt;. So next is to code the arduino such that on receiving a &lt;code&gt;True&lt;/code&gt;from the PIR, the arduino would close the switch, activating the relay to close the switch of the fan, and stay like that for a couple of minutes. I didn&#39;t want it to go on-off every 3 seconds, hence the timeout.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Next was mounting all of it together. A breadboard would&#39;ve been unsafe, &lt;a href=&quot;http://electronics.stackexchange.com/questions/19813/can-you-put-a-120vac-positive-line-into-a-breadboard&quot;&gt;as per the Internet&lt;/a&gt;, hence I bought a perfboard for the purpose. I soldered everything to its place, and the final result was something like the following. Oh but first, some code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The code which was shamelessly ripped off Arduino.cc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/800a4cbc44150d9e777936edde912680.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Here is how it looked [Heavy images. Patience!]&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pir/pir2.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pir/pir4.jpeg&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pir/pir5.jpeg&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My desk that beautiful day!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pir/pir1.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Now &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Adirockzz95/TARS&quot;&gt;Aditya&lt;/a&gt; would&#39;ve told you that this project is what electronics people do when they&#39;re like 5. Nevertheless, I was too proud of this. Not just because I could do it, but because I needed it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So did it work? No. The range of the PIR sensor was a bit too small for the entire room, and I had to literally dance in front of it to trigger it. Solution? Multiple PIRs to cover the entire room. Also, I realized how easily I could just add the tubelight to the same circuit. Just add another relay and connect it to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.in/LDR-Light-Dependent-Register-resistor/dp/B018LJPI76&quot;&gt;LDR&lt;/a&gt; sensor and set it to trigger when the daylight fell below a certain threshold. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Suddenly, automating stuff in the room seemed a bit too simple, and it really is, even for an electronics novice like myself. The Internet gives you that power. As always, thank you for reading, and pardon any silly technical mistakes that I must&#39;ve made in the post (even better, correct me ;).
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>College Vs Startup - Working On Projects</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/08/college-vs-startup.html"/>
   <updated>2016-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/08/college-vs-startup</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	First of all, wishing all you fellow Indians a very happy 70th Independence Day. This day is very dear to the hearts of us Indians, and although I enjoy watching the Republic Day parade more, I certainly enjoy seeing the beautiful tricolors all around the place. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I was asked to compile a list of all the differences between working on a project in a startup and doing the same in college. Of course, we have projects every semester the way (some) startups have products, and we are made to follow some guidelines while developing these projects (like planning, documentation and testing methodologies), but there are some subtle differences. Here is a paste of all the points I wrote at that time. I thought it would make for a useful read for some of you. It is about an organization, addressed to a real person and talks about some other people too, if you were wondering about the names involved, and trimmed to only the parts that matter here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Differences between college and startup projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		The most important factor for me were the stakes involved. In college, making a mistake or leaving some edge cases incomplete were quite acceptable since we were the users of the product. Here at Fourthlion, since a lot of people are involved in making a project happen, plus the people we pitch the product to are some high level state officials, the margin of error tolerated is reduced. That actually brings out the best in you, since you have to push your limits in order to accomplish the new quality standards that you never knew existed.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		The second factor is deadlines. There are deadlines in college projects, but the deadlines aren&#39;t connected to further set of events. Here at Fourthlion, me completing a project on, say Monday is directly linked with the product getting pitched on Tuesday, and that sense of responsibility makes you want to meet those deadlines to avoid wasting other people&#39;s time.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		Then there are people around you. They know how to make things work. For example, Sukhpreet. I learnt what it is like to be organized, from him. He writes down each and everything in his diary or in a spreadsheet. I bought a diary just to get that habit, and it is already helping. I saw what serious documentation looked like when working on the first project, made by him. I understood how important initial user feedbacks are, which I had never taken ever in my life till now. These are the things Fourthlion taught me even though I had never planned to learn them. This is what I feel is the effect of working with great people. You try to copy them, and acquire their good habits.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		You get to know how much can be accomplished in a day. In college, if someone asks me how much time will it take to complete this product, I&#39;d say I don&#39;t know. Because there are a lot of different things that a student does apart from the project. Here, I have a fairly good estimate on what I can do in the 8-10 hours of work everyday, and hence I can give you a good estimate of how much time the project/component should take based past estimates.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		 There&#39;s a good deal of pressure working here that I never felt in college. A reason for that could be there&#39;s real people&#39;s real money and time involved. The pressure actually feels bad at first, but just looking a week back, I hardly think I would&#39;ve been able to accomplish whatever I did, if there was no pressure involved.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		At this startup, the users are real people who just want a beautiful working product and don&#39;t really care about the cutting edge tech stack I use, which wasn&#39;t the case until now. That has given me a new way to think about the code I write, the more user oriented way. And since I am the only person editing and adding code, I feel much connected to the project than otherwise would have, which is not necessarily a good thing in the real world with multiple developers collaborating.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		About DoNew, I&#39;d honestly admit that I didn&#39;t really see the point of sending updates on what I do, initially. But I like to take leaps of faith when the people involved know much more about how things work than I do. Now when I think, I feel like the updates were more for myself than they were for you and others. I feel I have started to keep a track of my own progress through the updates, which has formed a habit. Just to give you an idea, after writing the update to you, I write myself a personal update in a diary, with things I did wrong and things I can improve upon. It has made a great deal of difference to me personally. And I don&#39;t think I will ever break this habit of tracking my own progress and shortcomings.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		When I was skeptic about whether I would be able to handle the real world development here at Fourthlion back when I was in Mumbai, you told me to try, build, make mistakes and to believe that you can. That &#39;believing that you can&#39; has been an important part. For example, when I heard about integrating Asana and building a project on top of it that people can use, I was a bit scared. But I made my mind to keep working as much as I could with all dedication and not really worry about the end result. And now, slowly but steadily, it is taking shape of a practical app, which I am really proud of!
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		Lastly, the importance of having a mentor. I didn&#39;t understand it before when I read about people having mentor. I don&#39;t need to say much about this one now!
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	As always, thank you for reading!
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Project Lumos Experience</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/07/the-project-lumos-experience.html"/>
   <updated>2016-07-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/07/the-project-lumos-experience</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	This thing started about a year ago, and I didn&#39;t write about it because I haven&#39;t thought about it, or probably didn&#39;t think it was that significant part of me. But today, when I look back, it probably was the best thing I ever did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Let us go back and see how it all happened, and how it shaped me into becoming a better version of me. It started in the first week of September, 2015, just before our Engineers&#39; Day celebration. I came to college one day, when Ankit, my buddy, was looking for me. Without me asking, he told me that some senior has come and he was quite unhappy with the preparations. Then he dropped the bomb. &quot;He was looking for our technical head&quot;. I was supposed to be in college by 9 am, and I wasn&#39;t there even by 1. And yes, I was the technical head. Damn! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Okay, I thought, I&#39;ll have to face him. I was scared. One of my biggest disappointments with myself is that I don&#39;t act even though I know things are not going very well. I knew the Engineers&#39; Day was all fun and no tech, but I didn&#39;t really care at that point.  I just preferred to &#39;go with the flow&#39; and mind my own stuff. Maybe that was the reason I was scared. I was scared because I wasn&#39;t taking up the responsibility. I was scared because I still acted like a kid. I was scared because I took a position in the committee that I knew I didn&#39;t deserve.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Anyway, I thought. Let&#39;s face it. I met him. His name was Abhishek. Abhishek Juneja. Oh nice, same name, awesome, I thought. We started the conversation, and he was not that scary anymore. In fact, he was cool. Totally cool. He spoke about things (read &lt;i&gt;technical things&lt;/i&gt;) that only 2 other people in the entire college I know, could speak of. Super cool. He knew his stuff well, and he gave us pointers about the things that we could organize in our college like seminars on various topics. I wrote them on a piece of paper, and kept that with me for the next 6 months, not doing a single thing from it. I was never a person who could act, as I said. I always was someone who wants to act, wants to change, wants to achieve, but never does. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The meeting with Abhishek lasted some 2 odd hours. I remember my friends waiting for me on the stairs. They didn&#39;t ask much about it. We went home and delivered a great Engineers&#39; Day later. That piece of paper in my bag occasionally reminded me of Abhishek, but that was it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Fast forward to December 2015. Last exam of the fifth semester, I was all in the mood to go home fast and start working on the startup that was getting delayed since it began in August. Cherrylogs. Outside the college, Manas, our GS (short for General Secretary) gave me a quick update. &#39;Abhishek wants to talk to you and me.&#39;. Hmm, interesting. &#39;Maybe Abhishek is coming to our college for some seminar, like he said&#39;, I thought. The call happened, and Abhishek, along with someone else I don&#39;t remember now (I think it was Prashant), explained to us how our syllabus and technical education is not enough for students passing out to actually work in the industry. It was true, but how could this call help. Then he laid his master plan to make a portal, a knowledge portal where students can find resources to learn anything they wish to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	That idea was, for me, fundamentally flawed. Why would someone who doesn&#39;t bother to Google his/her interests, visit the portal to get links to resources that Google would&#39;ve otherwise easily provided anyways. I kept telling him that. It was not a very positive call, and quite honestly, I just couldn&#39;t understand what Abhishek meant half of the times. Slow grasper, I am.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	At the back of my head, I was trying to figure out what is this guy&#39;s motive. Has he heard about Google Adsense recently and got real excited? Does he want to shine his CV? Is he hiring for some startup he has just started? What can it be?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	We spoke for sometime, and the explanations from Abhishek were not helping me understand the gist of the project. At the end, it was decided that with or without us, they are going to build the portal, and that would be it. I think we (me and Abhishek) had some more calls after that. I told him that I have to visit my native place (which I was visiting after a long gap of 2 years, first time after getting into Engineering), where I wouldn&#39;t be able to work, and even after that I had my startup, Cherrylogs, to focus on. That was rude, selfish and arrogant. But then, I just didn&#39;t understand the point of making that portal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Fast forward to first week of January 2016. I am near a beach in someplace, Karnataka, enjoying the holidays, and I get a call from Abhishek. He expected me to get home by now, but few more days is what I tell him. He asks me again, would you work and help us build this thing. I reply in negative, same reasons repeated again. The call drops due to some reception problems, and then no more calls are made after that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I come back home, start usual college, and around mid January, I am told that a &#39;seminar is going to be held by our seniors&#39;. Cool. &#39;It is Abhishek Juneja,...It is on 23rd&#39;. Oh damn. I had planned for a trek to Sandhan Valley on the same day. I wouldn&#39;t be able to make it. It was publicized by our committee, and I, a &lt;i&gt;member&lt;/i&gt;, wasn&#39;t available on that day. I felt bad, but then forgot about it. The seminar went well, and I heard about it from people. So apparently Abhishek had built the portal all by himself, managing his office work at the same time. Good for them, I thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Days went by, and I had completely forgotten about the project. I had seen the website Abhishek made, and it was good. Not much to it, looked fairly static. Sometime in mid February, Dhananjay calls me out of my classroom for a conversation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	If there is one person I respect the most in my college, it is Dhananjay. He&#39;s simple, friendly, thoughtful, humble, helpful and technically fluent enough that we had great conversations with each other without losing out on what the other guy is saying. This was particularly important because there are just two people in the entire college with whom I can have a heart to heart technical talk without dumbing down on the details. And he was good at teaching. Many people are experts in their fields. But very few can share their knowledge in a way people learn and enjoy learning. Dhananjay is one such guy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I go out to speak to him, and he asks me about Project Lumos and the conversations I had with Abhishek Juneja. Told him everything I remembered of. He then explained me certain things, and although I don&#39;t remember what are the things that he said, what I do remember is that the chat with him gave me the feeling that this is something important and I have to be a part of it. I remember telling him that doing it all alone won&#39;t be feasible for me, to which he said, &lt;i&gt;&#39;Don&#39;t worry. We&#39;ll form a team&#39;&lt;/i&gt;. And that was it. Single most value adding decision that I had taken for myself in a while. If that seemed like an overstatement, continue reading.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The next couple of weeks were team creation, planning and a lot of things which I don&#39;t need to get into the details of. It was fun. We had weekly calls to report the status to Abhishek. He was the Project Manager for us. Dhananjay was good at conveying the messages from Abhishek to the team of 15 odd enthusiastic people that we formed. We also started weekly sessions on random technical topics to talk on in front of the team, so that they pick up faster. All in all, I was enjoying the experience. It was also due to Project Lumos that I can speak better in public. Seeing Abhishek and Dhananjay do it gave me that confidence needed. The way to teach is also something I&#39;ll credit Dhananjay for teaching me. He is probably the best teacher I&#39;ve known. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	During this period, we had several meetings with the faculty for discussions over computer lab approvals, certificates for students participating and other stuff. It was during this time that I got to know Dhananjay and Abhishek closely. I always had a guilt that I don&#39;t know my seniors well. Especially with someone like Dhananjay as a senior, I felt that I should talk to them more often, interact with them, learn from their experiences and more. I never actually did that, and I always felt bad that I didn&#39;t know any of the seniors personally. That changed with this project. I got to know Dhananjay and Abhishek well, and that was a proud feeling for me. Yes, I know two of the best seniors one can get, and I am very lucky for that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	With the help of Dhananjay, we got in touch with Rahul Kulkarni, who later became my mentor for learning and implementing Data Science and who pushed me into this internship in Delhi at Fourthlion. The influence Rahul Kulkarni has on me is not something I can put into words here. I have learned a lot from him, during these days and later when I&#39;ll go for my internship.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Towards the end of the semester, some more people joined in, but most never actually work with us or joined us in any sessions. Exams started and we all partially disconnected to prepare for exams. My last exam was on 26th May, while the second year folks had their last exam on 10th June I suppose. It was only after that, that any actual work was to begin. But then, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2016/06/sixth-semester-and-then.html&quot;&gt;some things happened&lt;/a&gt; and I came to Delhi for the internship. Ten of the students, along with Abhishek and Dhananjay went on to build a knowledge portal that went fairly well, considering that the students working on it were building their first project. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Today, 25th of July. Four more days to the end of my internship. I am thinking about the number of things I have learned in the last six months. Insane. I have learned how to talk to people, how to talk in public, how to teach, how to listen, how to manage time, energy and utilize it efficiently, explored widest of the technology domains, created and deployed some good applications, got a state&#39;s chief minister see the application I made, visited Agra, Taj Mahal, traveled in an aeroplane, made numerous great contacts at Fourthlion, met Sukhpreet who is one of the best individuals I have had the fortune of knowing. Damn! All of this, each and every one of it was because I agreed to work for Project Lumos with Abhishek and Dhananjay. Is it fair to say now, and in no way an exaggeration, that agreeing to it was probably one of the best decisions I had ever taken for myself, if not the best.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	It is quite late, but it is now that I have understood Abhishek well. He is one of the jewels that is yet to be discovered by someone. He has had his past, but the things that he has achieved ever since, amazing. He is honest to the core, straightforward and never thinks once before appreciating or criticizing someone. He rather undervalues himself, for he thinks he has something less than that what most people do. The fact is, he is far richer in his attitude and character than most people I know, helpful, hardworking and selfless. In the end, I think this is what matters. Skilled human-robots are dime a dozen these days. Attitude is what separates the individual from the herd, and he&#39;s kind of a guy you see and say, &#39;Dude, he&#39;s going to make it big in life&#39;. Yes, exactly that kind of a guy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I need not say more, for I have poured my thoughts into this piece. This came out because of an email that Abhishek sent out on Saturday, and I kept thinking, this guy has no damn clue how much of an influence he has on our lives. So Abhishek, and Dhananjay, this one&#39;s for you. If you ever read this, know that you are SUPER AWESOME and SUPER COOL! Your fan forever, Abhishek.
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sixth Semester And Then</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/06/sixth-semester-and-then.html"/>
   <updated>2016-06-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/06/sixth-semester-and-then</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
  I intended to write this long ago, at least a month ago. But then, I am doing it now. Even now, to be honest, I am writing this to just to save my per-month-an-article-streak. So here I am, sixth semester and then.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Semester 6, especially the end of it was too much fun. For one, my friend Aditya had returned, two, I got an interesting mentorship under which I had started to learn data science, and then, the exams were really good. Then there was Project Lumos, something to look forward to after the exams. All set. But life took a sharp turn, when on May 25th, I was offered an internship at Fourthlion by Rahul sir, my mentor for the data science learning. It was a shock, a good one, and I replied in affirmative after talking to my parents, friends and my project lumos buddies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next two days came and went like anything. Bought a couple of new tshirts and other essential things. Got the room set for the next two months, got flight ticket and I was all ready to launch. It was very, very exciting. I have not travelled a lot, and going to a new city, like Delhi, in an aeroplane for the very first time was a dream, coming true. I left on 29th, reached my room at 8 in the evening. It was all good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The next one month proved to be one of the best of my life. I have enjoyed a lot, learnt a lot, interacted with people a lot, made a lot of new friends, and built some really cool products. I just couldn&#39;t have thought all of this when I was in my hometown.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I am exactly one month into this internship, and one more to go. I am looking forward to more fun, more work and more amazing people to meet in this one. Also, I will publish all that I have written for myself in this month here, because there are a lot of things worth sharing, good and bad experiences, differences between working in a startup and in college and many more. Countless. Thank you for reading!
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>_Generic in C And Generic LinkedList Implementation</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/05/_generic-in-C.html"/>
   <updated>2016-05-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/05/_generic-in-C</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
  Tada! Finally a non-Javascript post for those of you who stopped visiting my blog because of my sick Js addiction. So my lost friend Aditya is back, and while talking to him, I got to read a piece of code that he wrote when we were in third semester, last year. The aim was to build a generic container to store different datatypes, in C. So yes, literally storing [21, &quot;abhishek&quot;, 3.142, &#39;z&#39;] in a single dynamically allocated linkedlist. That was pretty bold for us then.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  For making that happen, he made use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C11_(C_standard_revision)#Changes_from_C99_&quot;&gt;_Generic&lt;/a&gt; macro that C11 introducted for generic type selection. For those unfamiliar with it, I&#39;ll begin with explaining the basics of the macro. For those of you interested in the linkedlist code, scroll down to the bottom of this article. You can always check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg14/www/docs/n1570.pdf&quot;&gt;C11 draft [section 6.5.1.1 Generic selection pg #96]&lt;/a&gt; (the standard costs around $60 but is essentially the same thing).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	 The _Generic macro follows the format &lt;code&gt;_Generic(controlling-expression, association-list)&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;i&gt;controlling-expression&lt;/i&gt; is the expression whose type is to be detected, and &lt;i&gt;association-list&lt;/i&gt; is the dictionary of type-expression pairs where type can be any object type and the expression can be any expression, constant or a pointer to any function, pretty much anything that can be evaluated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	To put it simply, compare it to the switch statement for type detection. For example,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;
int main() {
  char *teststring = &quot;my char array&quot;; // target object
  char *type = _Generic(
    teststring,
    int: &quot;int&quot;,
    int*: &quot;int *&quot;,
    char: &quot;char&quot;,
    char*: &quot;char *&quot;,
    float: &quot;float&quot;,
    default: &quot;default&quot;
  );
  printf(&quot;%s&quot;, type);
  return 0;
}

~$ gcc main.c
~$ ./a.out
char *
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The _Generic macro can be wrapped around in a nice looking function call, say detect_type(). Compare this to a (pseudo) switch statement which evaluates the case that matches the switch params
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
// Pseudocode may resemble Javascript. Reader discretion advised
var someobj = &quot;text here&quot;; // target object
var type; // to store the typename
type_switch(someobj) {
  case int:
    type = &quot;int&quot;;
  case int*:
    type = &quot;int*&quot;;
  case char:
    type = &quot;char&quot;;
  case char*:
    type = &quot;char*&quot;;
  default:
    type = &quot;default&quot;;
}
print(type)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So that is it. A compile time type identification in C with a simple macro. We can do pretty amazing stuff with it using pointers to functions. For example, a generic print function, that can take in any type of argument and print it. I have added cases for integers, characters and string, but others can be added just as easily.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/3887df927f2d913c03704cac3ddaa9fc.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	That was neat, wasn&#39;t it. Now back to Aditya. He used the same macro to create a dynamically allocated linkedlist. I am pasting the gist here so that you can read his beautiful code.
  &lt;button id=&quot;btn&quot;&gt;Show Code&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;vector&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;File &lt;b&gt;linkedlist.c&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/0699d92bb972320e33b3cee8f81abc23.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;File &lt;b&gt;linkedlist.h&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/6175447dd928d4c46bdc7f51b90c8b33.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;File &lt;b&gt;main.c&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/cacf3b03483759c02e997afe13aa3373.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	To compile it, run &lt;pre&gt;~$ gcc main.c linkedlist.c -o linkedlist&lt;/pre&gt; on any machine with GCC installed (I&#39;ve tested it on version &amp;gt;4.9). Run it with &lt;pre&gt;~$ ./linkedlist&lt;/pre&gt; and you should see the different elements that we&#39;ve added printed on the standard out. You may also pack the linkedlist into a statically linked library, by running.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
~$ gcc -c linkedlist.c -o linkedlist.o
~$ ar rcs linkedlist.a linkedlist.o
~$ gcc main.c linkedlist.a
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Interesting, isn&#39;t it? Want to thank him, or have any comments or improvements? Drop them into the comment box. Thank you for reading.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;External Links&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSGH2K_13.1.0/com.ibm.xlc131.aix.doc/language_ref/genericselection.html&quot;&gt;IBM KB article on generic selector&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertgamble.net/2012/01/c11-generic-selections.html?m=1&quot;&gt;Robert Gamble&#39;s blog post: c11 generic selections&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9804371/syntax-and-sample-usage-of-generic-in-c11&quot;&gt;Stackoverflow question: syntax and sample usage of generic in c11&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
  document.getElementById(&#39;vector&#39;).style.display = &#39;none&#39;;
  document.getElementById(&#39;btn&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, function showVec() {
    document.getElementById(&#39;vector&#39;).style.display = &#39;block&#39;;
  });
&lt;/script&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Being Stupid</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/being-stupid.html"/>
   <updated>2016-04-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/being-stupid</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
  So my struggle with long distance trains doesn&#39;t seem to stop. This time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2016/01/The-Midnight-Symphony.html&quot;&gt;just like the last time&lt;/a&gt;, my train got late. By 30 days. And I am to be blamed for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Like Will Smith says in &#39;The Persuit Of Happiness&#39;, &#39;this part of my life is called &lt;i&gt;being stupid&lt;/i&gt;&#39;, after trusting a hippie with his expensive scanner and realizing how bad a decision it was. I had the exact same feelings this morning about myself. Let&#39;s rewind two weeks. I had to book train tickets for attending a wedding function at my native place, Karwar, on 29th April. As always, I did so from the irctc.co.in portal, and got three confirmed seats for May 28th. Awesome, I said, knowing how hard it is to get tickets during the holiday season. Got the confirmation email with all details and I was good to go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Today, in the morining, we were all set. All dressed up and ready to start our day journey. We don&#39;t usually do day travels since it is too hot in the non air conditioned coaches that we usually book our tickets in. Anyways, it was going to be fun, I thought. Called up the railway enquiry number 139 to make sure train was on time. Surprisingly, it said the charts weren&#39;t prepared yet. Odd, because the train left the originating station a full day ago. Must be a technical glitch, I thought. Made sure I took everything; Misty, mobile phone, charger, water bottle and what not. Great. We left for our train that was scheduled to be departured at 08:10 in the morning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The station is just a few kilometers away. We reached there at 8 sharp. Reaching there, I immediately started to look for the platform where our train was expected to arrive. The indicator didn&#39;t say anything. Must be a fairly new train, I thought, trying to bury the little doubt I was starting to have. Let&#39;s ask the station master, said my uncle, and so we went to the station master, to get some solid confirmation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The station master&#39;s office was a large room with a table in the center. More like a bollywood movie&#39;s police station. The man there was wearing his shirt then. We entered and he asked us what was the matter. I asked him about the status of our train, numbered 22656. He thought for a second before quicky replying that the train only ran on saturdays. Damn! That wasn&#39;t possible. I had a reserved ticket in that same train and it showed today&#39;s date. Station master asked us for the ticket. I showed him the eticket on my mobile phone. Now he was confused. He called up someone on his intercom and asked if there was this particular train running today. The other guy said the same thing, this train only runs on saturdays. Umm. Weird. Station master tried to confirm it by asking if there was any additions to its trips. The answer must have been in negative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Now we three were real confused. We tried to reason the possbile explanations. &#39;Maybe the train is so new that even the station master doesn&#39;t know about it&#39;, said my uncle. Meanwhile the station master rang another number, this time of the previous station, called &#39;Vasai Road&#39;. He asked if any train with the said number had left the station or is scheduled to leave. No, was the reply. We thought for another few seconds when suddenly, with a little frustration in his decenly polite voice, the station master said, &#39;This ticket is for 28th May&#39;. I went silent for five full seconds. With my tongue stuck out, all I could say there was &lt;i&gt;&#39;sorry sir&#39;&lt;/i&gt;. I and my uncle came out silently, glad that he didn&#39;t swear at our stupidity. Okay, MY stupidity. We came out, and had the greatest burst of laughter. For him, it was funny. For me, a little less towards funny and a lot more towards the incoming embarassment. I, with my 17 years of schooling, couldn&#39;t tell May from April. Stupid. Very, very stupid. We went to where my parents were waiting. I told them, smiling and trying to make a poker face simultaneously. My mom, got so furious that she actually started to laugh. Things were pretty serious, and yet somehow, that was so stupid that no one knew how to react.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We thought for some time then, and decided to go in some other train in the unreserved compartment, which, if you know, you know the struggle and if you don&#39;t, you&#39;re pretty lucky and rich. I am still in the train, tired, sleepy and dirty with sweat and dirt all over me. I&#39;ll reach in three or four hours, and then it will be life a usual.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Googling And Asking Better Questions</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/googling-life.html"/>
   <updated>2016-04-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/googling-life</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
  Like many of the things you do in your lives, Googling is an art. Getting to the right page that you were looking for, with the right set keywords and clicking the right links, all this seems to be quite random and uncertain, but once you get into the groove, things become natural and predictable. Finding that random song you heard on the street is no big deal, and neither is finding the article that you had read couple of years ago, the only part of which you remember was the author&#39;s last name. Information is growing each day, and having the right set of tools always within you is so much important. Yes, there&#39;s that shiny history feature in you latest Chromium browser with sync, so that you never lose your tracks, but knowing how to find something on a totally random public PC without having to look into your history is very convenient, also cool.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  But then, you might ask, what is the point of remembering a whole new set of rules just so that I could type in proper queries on Google&#39;s homepage? Yeah, if you think about it this way, not much. Every other site has a search functionality built into it. But, think. Googling for a computer problem with &lt;code&gt;site:stackoverflow.com&lt;/code&gt; and searching the same problem on stackoverlow&#39;s search is somewhat different. Stackoverflow doesn&#39;t invest as much time on search optimization as Google does. That is the case when stackoverflow&#39;s search is one of the best you can find on the Internet. Think about others. Now, every site having its own search has its own small set of advance search syntax. Would you go around memorizing rules from each and every site that you visit? Are you not better off memorizing for just one site and using it to find everything else? In my opinion, yes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  And learning how to google or how to search in general doesn&#39;t just mean memorizing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_hacking&quot;&gt;dorks&lt;/a&gt;, although it does certainly help. It generally means asking better questions. What does that mean? Well, in general, the more you research before asking a question, the more are the chances of you getting a proper and to the point answer. That doesn&#39;t just apply to online searches, but also when asking for help to your fellow classmate or colleague. The research helps in a number of ways. Firstly and most importantly, it can spare you the need to ask for help by finding the answer yourself. Secondly, research also helps to properly understand your problem&#39;s causes, such that any similar problem can be solved with the same approach. Thirdly, it creates a psychological difference in the mind of the answerer when he or she reads a &lt;i&gt;&quot;this code doesn&#39;t work&quot;&lt;/i&gt; and a &lt;i&gt;&quot;this code throws a undefined variable error on line 42&quot;&lt;/i&gt; and a &lt;i&gt;&quot;the &#39;name&#39; variable on line 42 is undefined as the async function on the previous line hasn&#39;t returned yet.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;. As you see for yourself, the third problem definition is far more probable to get answered, and the first one is likely to get ignored (or worse, downvoted, if you&#39;re on StackExchange).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I have people who send me program source code files in emails and the only line of text inside of the email being the obvious title that &#39;the code doesn&#39;t work&#39;. That is where the problem lies. When all you say is &#39;it doesn&#39;t work&#39;, then the only reply that you deserve is &#39;congratulations on figuring that out&#39;. It&#39;s that simple. And to understand the importance of it, you need to value the time of others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So how does one turn from a naive help addict to his or her own problem solver? The answer is simple, know what the problem is and start searching for already answered questions. You always have documentations and manuals at your disposal, but let&#39;s face it, it is not easy to get hold of manuals if you&#39;re new to the subject. And even if you&#39;re well versed with the topic in hand, you can always save time by searching the popular forums first. So what do you do? You search for the exact problem message, or keyword, keeping it as concise as possible. Trust me, the query string is all that matters, because rarely you&#39;ll encounter a problem that somebody else didn&#39;t face and asked somewhere. You want to keep the variable count low, and so if you&#39;re learning A, use popular libraries and operating systems B and C that would keep the entropy factor low. As an example, if I&#39;m not hacking into linux core and simply programming Javascript, I prefer to use Debian and Nodejs stable, &lt;i&gt;just to make sure that when I fall into a ditch, the ditch is a popular one&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In case you still didn&#39;t get a working solution, now start to dig into documents and manuals. It is usually the case when the component that you think is broken, isn&#39;t actually broken. Look out for platform specific notes and details. Troubleshoot your way backwards to the line where your code broke. If you manage to find that out, then you know the problem. Start by making a fresh google search for that error. In most of the cases, a forum thread might have the answer, which you can find easily with [SOLVED] in their titles. There are also many instances when if you are working with an open source dependency, you&#39;ll find the issue raised by somebody on the project issues section of their repository [like github issues page]. Reading those has helped me countless times.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  If even then, in the rare (very rare with computer problems) case that you still haven&#39;t found a solution for your problem in the online forums and documentations, start by properly defining the problem. It is time to ask for help. Always, ALWAYS remember, the people you&#39;re asking questions to, are busy people. If you want to have a percent chance of getting your question read by experts, value their time. The essential things that must be included in every help request are,
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Precise problem definition with the problem and the current and expected results.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Steps to reproduce it. Code snippet that points the line of error (You should never paste 200 lines of code into the question).
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      What have you tried yet. List of the things that didn&#39;t work out.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      The platform you&#39;re running, everything relevant to the problem. More the detail, better is the understanding of your situation by the reader.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      A paste of your latest logs relevant to the error. Learn to use pastebin like sites to paste large text files.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      The links to those similar problem-answers that didn&#39;t work for you.
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
  Add or remove things depending upon the situation. It may or may not apply every time. Important thing here is, try to be a problem solver. Don&#39;t be part of the problem, but try to be part of the possible solution. It is okay if no one answers, but hang there for the first 30 minutes at least, in case someone asks for more details that you didn&#39;t provide.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  This should really answer your question, and in case not, don&#39;t lose hope. There are hundreds of specialized forums that you can head to, if the problem is that important to you. Back to Googling, what is it that some people better at finding stuff on the Internet than others? Now you know the answer to that. See, this is how it generally works. Most good questions are answered. Now that you know how good questions are asked, you know what is inside them. You can make a pretty educated guess about what an existing question may contain. Now your task is as simple as just using those keywords to find that answer. This works. Trust me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Concluding it, I hope this post was informative. Ask wise questions. People really appreciate when you ask good questions. They say no question is stupid. That is not an excuse to not trying to search from the existing resources, or being a naive help addict. Keep exploring.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>WebSockets</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/websockets.html"/>
   <updated>2016-04-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/websockets</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	If you&#39;re like me, then you must have gone nuts on hearing about &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebSockets_API&quot;&gt;WebSockets&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. We now have a totally independent protocol that will not terminate connection after a request-response cycle, which means all hacks to keep a persistent connection from the browser (long polling, I&#39;m looking at you) would now be part of the history. Welcome to the world of WebSockets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Let&#39;s start with the Wikipedian and Mozillian definition of WebSockets, to get some initial traction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Wikipedia says that..&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
	WebSocket is a protocol providing full-duplex communication channels over a single TCP connection. The WebSocket protocol was standardized by the IETF as RFC 6455 in 2011, and the WebSocket API in Web IDL is being standardized by the W3C.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Mozilla Developer Network says that..&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
	WebSockets is an advanced technology that makes it possible to open an interactive communication session between the user&#39;s browser and a server. With this API, you can send messages to a server and receive event-driven responses without having to poll the server for a reply.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	To begin with, let us all make sure we have websocket support by clicking &lt;button id=&quot;hasBtn&quot; onclick=&quot;hasSocket();&quot;&gt;here&lt;/button&gt;. Assuming you do, let&#39;s begin. Web browsers provide us with the &lt;code&gt;WebSocket&lt;/code&gt; class. To create a websocket, we simply need to &lt;pre&gt;let ws = new WebSocket(&#39;ws://server.com/endpoint&#39;);&lt;/pre&gt;This gives us a &lt;i&gt;websocket&lt;/i&gt; object which supports methods like send() and close() and event listeners like onmessage and onerror.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Creating a nodejs instance running a websocket server is easy with modules. I did try to do it natively, but it went too tedious. Finally I settled for &lt;code&gt;ws&lt;/code&gt; module from npm. The server side code looks trival.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/d94830c3901b48ebdeb8375b37d0ee60.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	On the browser, things are even simpler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// call the object constructor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;WebSocket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;ws://nagekar-ws.herokuapp.com/&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// attach a message listener&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;onmessage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// send some message&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;hello server!&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Once we call the constructor, an HTTP GET request is generated to initiate the transaction. You&#39;ll find that these headers are sent by your browser.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;

GET / HTTP/1.1
Host: nagekar-ws.herokuapp.com
Connection:Upgrade
Pragma:no-cache
Sec-WebSocket-Extensions:permessage-deflate; client_max_window_bits
Sec-WebSocket-Key:ut0NjBQxxBnmtUStHfMUDw==
Sec-WebSocket-Version:13
Upgrade:websocket
User-Agent:Mozilla/5.0 (X11; Linux x86_64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/49.0.2623.108 Safari/537.36
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The ones to notice are the URL, which begins with ws:// protocol. &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/23674199/why-is-there-no-same-origin-policy-for-websockets-why-can-i-connect-to-ws-loc#comment36372038_23674863&quot;&gt;Cross domain requests&lt;/a&gt; are allowed. This initial step requires the use of HTTP(S) or web, hence the name &#39;web&#39; sockets. The &lt;i&gt;&#39;Connection:Upgrade&#39;&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;&#39;Upgrade:websocket&#39;&lt;/i&gt; and what requests the server to change this connection to a socket one. The &lt;i&gt;Sec-WebSocket-Key&lt;/i&gt; header is what client sends to the server. The server crafts another key with this and returns it back in the response header. A response header looks like this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
HTTP/1.1 101 Switching Protocols
Connection:Upgrade
Sec-Websocket-Accept:7CAJHdL7QMG4ceqd0M1O8SDbM2Q=
Sec-Websocket-Extensions:permessage-deflate
Upgrade:websocket
Via:1.1 vegur
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	On receiving the &lt;i&gt;Sec-Websocket-Accept&lt;/i&gt; header, the handshake is completed, and now the client and server are connected via persistent sockets, ready to perform both way message delivery.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Click &#39;Connect&#39; button to initiate WebSocket handshake. The server will respond with a timestamp every 2500 milliseconds. Also, the server will echo back everything to send at it. The close button will call the WebSocket.close() method which will terminate the connection.
	&lt;h4&gt;Message Box&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;div id=&quot;list&quot; style=&quot;height:100px;overflow-y:scroll;border:1px solid&quot;&gt;
	    &lt;ul id=&quot;msglist&quot;&gt;

	    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;
	    &lt;button id=&quot;connect&quot;&gt;Connect&lt;/button&gt;
	    &lt;input type=&quot;text&quot; id=&quot;inp&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;button id=&quot;send&quot;&gt;Send&lt;/button&gt;
		&lt;button id=&quot;close&quot;&gt;Close&lt;/button&gt;
	&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Pretty interesting, isn&#39;t it. Things get even more interesting when you use a readymade library built on top of WebSockets, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://socket.io&quot;&gt;Socket.io&lt;/a&gt;. It supports all browsers (through fallback to XHR/polling), has better looking APIs, is easy to use and allows you to broadcast without having to worry much about raw connections. If you&#39;re going to use these WebSockets in production, there&#39;s no reason not to use Socket.io. Using native websockets is not recommended if you&#39;re planning to support some legacy browsers. Even Mozilla terms it as an &#39;experimental technology&#39;. Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebSocket#Browser_compatibility&quot;&gt;compatibility table&lt;/a&gt; for more information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I hope this post was informative. I did learn a lot while researching on this topic, and I&#39;m glad I did. As always, thank you for reading. Please drop a comment in case of feedback or correction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/jquery/3.0.0-beta1/jquery.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
	function hasSocket() {
		if(window.WebSocket) {
			document.getElementById(&#39;hasBtn&#39;).innerHTML = &#39;Supported&#39;;
			document.getElementById(&#39;hasBtn&#39;).disabled = true;
		} else {
			document.getElementById(&#39;hasBtn&#39;).innerHTML = &#39;Not supported&#39;;
			document.getElementById(&#39;hasBtn&#39;).disabled = true;
		}
	}
	var ws;
	$(&#39;#connect&#39;).click(function() {
		ws = new WebSocket(&#39;wss://nagekar-ws.herokuapp.com/&#39;);
		ws.onmessage = function(msg) {
			$(&#39;#msglist&#39;).append(&#39;&lt;li style=&quot;color: green&quot;&gt;&#39; + msg.data + &#39;&lt;/li&gt;&#39;).focus();
			$(&#39;#list&#39;).scrollTop($(&#39;ul li&#39;).last().position().top + $(&#39;ul li&#39;).last().height());
		};
	});
	$(&#39;#send&#39;).click(function() {
		var msg = $(&#39;#inp&#39;).val();
		$(&#39;#msglist&#39;).append(&#39;&lt;li style=&quot;color: blue&quot;&gt;Message to server: &#39; + msg + &#39;&lt;/li&gt;&#39;).focus();
		$(&#39;#list&#39;).scrollTop($(&#39;ul li&#39;).last().position().top + $(&#39;ul li&#39;).last().height());
		ws.send(msg);
	});
	$(&#39;#close&#39;).click(function() {
		ws.close();
		$(&#39;#msglist&#39;).append(&#39;&lt;li style=&quot;color: red&quot;&gt;&#39; + &#39;Connection Closed&#39; + &#39;&lt;/li&gt;&#39;).focus();
		$(&#39;#list&#39;).scrollTop($(&#39;ul li&#39;).last().position().top + $(&#39;ul li&#39;).last().height());
	})
&lt;/script&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Event Driven Programming</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/event-driven-programming.html"/>
   <updated>2016-04-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/04/event-driven-programming</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	I remember starting to learn Javascript. It was all a nightmare. Functions used to execute out of order and seemed very random. There was chaos all around, and I was usually left wondering, &#39;what is the order of execution here?&#39;. Of course, that question never got answered, because that wasn&#39;t the right question. The right question would&#39;ve been, what drives these functions in this code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Fortunately, I asked it at an early stage. The things that make Javascript tick are called &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;events&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. Without these, your browser window is just a dead canvas. Not just the browser, but other Javascript environments as well, work because of events. And when you understand it, events and event driven programming are probably the most intuitive form of developing applications. Events are not difficult to visualize, once you start to relate them to the real world events.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Suppose you&#39;re alone at your home. You&#39;ll need to make sure you open the door in case someone arrives. There are two ways of doing it. First way is to periodically keep checking if someone is outside the door, say every 5 minutes. In the best case, someone will arrive the moment you open the door, but in the worst case, a visitor has to wait for about 5 minutes before you make your next visit. This is just ridiculous. It is inefficient (visitors have to wait for you) and waste of time (when you check but no one has arrived). Who does this? Well, most procedural languages work this way. And it works, for their use cases. But when you&#39;re dealing with real life scenarios, like checking doors or handling HTML form responses in browsers, where the time of completion of an action or arrival of a visitor is unknown, a better approach has to be used, especially when time, muscle and browser resources are so scarce. Here comes event driven programming.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Suppose, you&#39;re alone again, in the same house. But this time, you decide to make use of events. You install a doorbell. Now, whenever someone arrives and rings the bell, you know you have to go open the door. That&#39;s simple. That&#39;s event driven. It doesn&#39;t matter if the next visitor comes after a minute or after an hour. You&#39;ll open the door instantaneously, without waste of your own time. And the fact that most homes have doorbells and this is our natural workflow when dealing with similar situations, is the proof of how intuitive this programming paradigm is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Okay, that was cool, so far. But I know that I have to listen to a doorbell and then on hearing it, walk to the door to open it. How do I make the machine do that. The answer is callbacks. If you are not quite sure what they are or how they work, do check out my other article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nagekar.com/2016/02/callbacks-eventloop-in-javascript-explained.html&quot;&gt;how callbacks and event loop work&lt;/a&gt;. So essentially, we attach a &#39;callback&#39; to an event. The callback, as the name suggests, calls back when the event occurs, and lets us control the aftereffect. Such a callback is also called an event listener, which infact is what you attach to the &lt;code&gt;element.addEventListener(&#39;event&#39;, callback);&lt;/code&gt; when working in the DOM. In Nodejs environment, you get a custom EventEmitter class that you can use to emit and listen to events. If you haven&#39;t heard of it, &lt;a href=&quot;socket.io&quot;&gt;socket.io&lt;/a&gt; is all about custom events and the data transfer between the client and the server. It makes use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebSockets_API&quot;&gt;websockets&lt;/a&gt; along with XHRs. If you are into creating sockets and data interexchange between remote hosts like I am, socket.io is for you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/d5eb252e620ee157d4ab1cc49811221a.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Finally, I hope to have given you some insights of event driven programming with Javascript. Not a lot of code, but that is something you&#39;ll find everywhere. I always like to emphasis on the concepts rather than implementation. It makes for a better implementation.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gentoo Experience</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/03/gentoo-experience.html"/>
   <updated>2016-03-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/03/gentoo-experience</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	I started using GNU/Linux full time sometime in 2011. Before that, it was all tiny bits here and there, virtualbox and stuff like that. But then, I finally made my mind to replace the Windows based OS that I was running for Linux. Trust me, it was a very scary decision at that time, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.backtrack-linux.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Backtrack 5&lt;/a&gt; was my first full time Linux distro. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	From there, it was an ultimate goal to try out every major distro. I used Backtrack till version 5r3 when they dropped support. Then I tried Ubuntu, since I had read Backtrack was Ubuntu based. Switched to Kali Linux, for it was the latest. After that was CentOS 6. I remember using it because I had the same on my DigitalOcean VPS. VPS gone, it was time to switch. I tried Fedora, but GNOME 3 didn&#39;t appeal to me, and still at this point, I was unaware of what a desktop environment was, or how do I change one. Later I switched to Debian 7, which was when I fell in love with it. Attended the launch party of Debian 8 and started using it right away. Debian stable had some really outdated packages, and the GNOME environment didn&#39;t appeal to me either. I installed Debian testing, running XFCE. It was the setup I always needed and is still my daily driver. In the meantime, I tried OpenSUSE too, but nothing great. As you see, I don&#39;t really need a reason to switch distros.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	What really provoked me was a sentence that I read somewhere, &#39;if you have not used Slackware or Gentoo, you really have not used Linux&#39;. It was 3 years ago. Since then, I had multiple tries at installing Slackware, Gentoo and Arch, but somehow, I would mess some thing up and it would be a failure. You should note here that installing these systems is not as easy a task, especially when you don&#39;t understand the commands you are typing. This time was nothing different. I downloaded the ISO which was surprisingly just some ~250MBs. I burnt it to a disk and booted it up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The most scary part of it all is that there is no &#39;installer&#39;. You have to manually create partitions, the swap and the bootloader. Then there is the phase to download the &#39;stage3&#39; file to the root and untaring it. Chrooting into it, setting up a few things like network, downloading the kernel source, compiling it and adding it to the /boot directory and then the hardest stage. Reboot. Hard emotionally, that is. After a minute, you are either greeted by the login prompt, or you realize that the past 8 hours of your life went in vain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Luckily for me though, it booted up. It was after midnight when it booted up, and I was installing it since 2pm. I&#39;m a noob. It is not a lot different than other distros, if you know how to &lt;i&gt;make&lt;/i&gt; softwares. There is this package manager called &lt;i&gt;emerge&lt;/i&gt; which is helpful too (it downloads sources and builds it, resolving dependencies). I am currently running it command line, as I didn&#39;t setup the Xorg during installation. It is pretty usable, and the best part is that you actually understand your system. I realized that this is a great way to actually learn GNU/Linux. The thing that I have to live with is that since each and every installation is by compiling source, it is damn slow. Usually 15-30 minutes for most applications. The plus point is that since it is build on my particular system, the executable is smaller than usual (and I read it is faster too). Cool, right?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I am looking forward to using it everyday on my PC, at least for sometime till I get really good at it. Maybe then I&#39;ll try doing the same on my laptop, which would be nice. For now, I&#39;ll have to figure out a way to install Xorg. 
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Going Full Stack On Mobile</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/03/going-full-stack-on-mobile.html"/>
   <updated>2016-03-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/03/going-full-stack-on-mobile</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	I have been a part of numerous web projects, and after these many applications using multiple languages and frameworks, when my friend Kunal suggested that we should develop an Android application that would make use of a backend and stuff like that, I couldn&#39;t help but desperately show my excitement. I told my friends, family and even seniors about the thing I am working on. After all, it was my first time going full stack mobile.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	For clarifying things, I am still doing the backend. It is my little team that has gone full stack. On mobile. The application, called the &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;moodShare&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt; will enable a user to do few simple tasks like registering, logging in, adding friends, sharing statuses, reading statuses and stuff like that. Each task is made possible with a simple API that is made without much thought to future scaling. I know, that is really bad from my side. But then, I was too desperate to get an application up and running that I neglected a lot of issues that arose when we were developing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The application&#39;s backend was Mongo, Express and Node. We deployed it to Modulus.io but then this happened and we had to shift it to Heroku. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:48.2886904762% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BCifT2gGkAT/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Too poor to get a proper server... Crashing in 3..2..1 #javascript #nodejs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by Abhishek Nagekar (@abhisheknagekar) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2016-03-04T17:06:48+00:00&quot;&gt;Mar 4, 2016 at 9:06am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	And this was when we had around 4 live users. The code quality was poor, very poor. Trust me when I say it. 4 users were hitting the database around 7 times a second. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BCiVuS2GkNI/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beautiful sight of requests hitting the API server #javascript #nodejs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A video posted by Abhishek Nagekar (@abhisheknagekar) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2016-03-04T15:43:02+00:00&quot;&gt;Mar 4, 2016 at 7:43am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Then there were many other issues as well. For example, if you added a friend who had 400 status updates in his or her name before you added, your phone would notify you, well, 400 times. Literally. That was awful. Push notification was implemented in a way you write an infinite for loop to check if something has changed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	But hey, this was our first time. We did enjoy each and every second of the development (around 4 days), the bugs just as much. We did learn a lot from it. Before this project, messaging queue was just a name, Google Cloud Messaging was just another service that I knew nothing about, three or four HTTP status codes that I knew. The satisfaction of knowing more about these was worth it all. Lastly, we did not abandon the project. Our alpha version was pretty stiff and unusable. Hopefully, with better APIs, better hosting and material design on the frontend, we plan to rock with the beta version. Stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Screenshots&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
	#inline {
		display: inline-block;
		text-align: center;
	}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;inline&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/moodshare/moodshare1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/moodshare/moodshare1.png&quot; width=&quot;180px&quot; height=&quot;320px&quot; style=&quot;display: inline&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/moodshare/moodshare2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/moodshare/moodshare2.png&quot; width=&quot;180px&quot; height=&quot;320px&quot; style=&quot;display: inline&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;	
	&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/moodshare/moodshare3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/moodshare/moodshare3.png&quot; width=&quot;180px&quot; height=&quot;320px&quot; style=&quot;display: inline&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/1dqalax3rg9xhfo/moodshare.apk?dl=0&quot;&gt;The initail release of moodShare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/abhn/mood-share&quot;&gt;Backend code on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://moodshare.herokuapp.com&quot;&gt;Live API on Heroku&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script async defer src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Callbacks And Event Loop Explained</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/02/callbacks-eventloop-in-javascript-explained.html"/>
   <updated>2016-02-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/02/callbacks-eventloop-in-javascript-explained</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	Callbacks are the things that make writing Javascript fun. If you think you are better off writing Javascript the way you wrote C and Java, then you are not really feeling the essence of this beautiful language. I found it rather hard to get used to this style of programming, called affectionately as the non-blocking style. What is this difficult sounding technique, and how can you make use of it to write better code is what we&#39;re going to see in this little essay.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Starting with the most basic explanation of what a callback is. Suppose I have two functions A and B. Although I can execute both of them myself, what I can do is execute A and ask A to execute B for me. Yes, that is all there is to the callbacks thing. I have two functions, I execute one and then ask it to execute the other one for me. Simple.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	But, you might ask, why I would ever want to do such a thing. Well, think about it this way. Computer processing is way, way faster than any I/O in question, especially when the I/O is on the other side of the network (or globe, for that matter) which is usual in the case of most web applications. Now, if you write code such that it queries a remote (or local) database and uses those results to carry on further processing, it results in a bottleneck. The processor executes instructions in the order of nanoseconds. An I/O request to the disk or network takes a few milliseconds at best, or a million times more time than what a processor needs to do a single atomic task. So essentially writing code that waits for results from I/O is simply wastage of the precious CPU cycles that could&#39;ve been put to better use in the meantime.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	A callback is also of great use when you want to make a function, say A, do things according to the context by supplying a specialized function B at the runtime. For example,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/22fa7b521b4013c30bdd.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So let&#39;s get into some (pseudo) code. We will first see what it is like to write code without callbacks and blocking IO and then examine some issues. Then we will write the same code using callbacks and non-blocking IO and see if we have rectified (or at least mitigated) those issues.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/6b032655b0924b0ed301.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Now this code is blocked when the Javascript engine is waiting for the Mongodb query to execute and return. It may take a few milliseconds, and only after that does the control of the program moves to the next lines. If the database hangs up for any reason, then the response will never reach the end user, regardless of whether the login credentials were correct or not (or let the user know something went wrong). It may also happen that the Javascript engine continues the execution with &#39;undefined&#39; returned, resulting in falsy block being executed each time. Having addressed these problems, let us now write the asynchronous version of the same (pseudo) code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/c1f4527a33f92a304d7e.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The callback function in a way keeps waiting for the response from the database in the background white the flow of program is not interrupted. As soon as the reply comes, the code in the callback function is executed. That sounds neat. Wait a second. Didn&#39;t we all learn that Javascript is single threaded and does a single job at a time and what not? Then how is the callback supposed to listen when the browser is already executing the code below it? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	To understand that, you&#39;ll have to stop believing every thing you write in Javascript is Javascript. Yes, I mean it. Javascript is single threaded, but there is much more to Javascript than just a single &lt;b&gt;call stack&lt;/b&gt;. Ok first, what is a call stack. Whenever a javascript file is executed, the engine creates a context for the code to run. This is the global execution context. It sits at the bottom of the call stack. Whenever a new function is invoked (or &#39;called&#39;), a new execution context is pushed on top of the stack. After the execution completes, the execution context is popped off the stack. After the last line of code is interpreted, the global context is popped off the stack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Well and good. But what about that setTimeout function that you set for the next 10 seconds? And our own mongodb query. Where did those go? The setTimeout is actually a webAPI provided to us, the Javascript developers, by the browser. Similarly, our mongodb query command was not a Javascript thingy, but a C++ API from the Nodejs bag of goodies. These events are handled by their respective environment, and when they finish execution, they enter what is called the &lt;b&gt;callback queue&lt;/b&gt;. There, they wait until the call stack is completely empty. Once the call stack in empty (all Javascript code is done running), the &lt;b&gt;event loop&lt;/b&gt; kicks in, pushes the callback functions waiting in the call back queue on top of the stack, one by one. A great way to visualize what the above paragraph just said is to try it out yourself at &lt;a href=&quot;http://latentflip.com/loupe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;loupe by Philip Roberts&lt;/a&gt;. He&#39;s an amazing guy and you should totally check out his talks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So that was it for this little article. Hope to have helped you. Keep digging.
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>AJAX Loading</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/02/Ajax-Loading.html"/>
   <updated>2016-02-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/02/Ajax-Loading</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;Edit: The section below this has some major issues, that I only found out after pushing into github. Read edit section.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I always admired the sites which did not reload upon clicking links here and there, but simple gave me whatever I requested for, with grace. Sites like Facebook, Twitter and Youtube extensively use it, and the application hardly reloads after the initial reload. Here&#39;s my attempt on making something similar.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Firstly, I downloaded a free HTML template from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onlinecasinos.im/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Online Casinos&lt;/a&gt;. The links had to be edited. The pattern I used was to replace, for example, any (internal) link pointing to &lt;code&gt;example.html&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;#/example.html&lt;/code&gt;. What it did was 1.) prevent the page from reloading, and 2.) putting the requested location to some place from where I can extract it with Javascript.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Next, grab that location of the hash. The Javascript&#39;s built in method &lt;code&gt;window.location.hash&lt;/code&gt; provides the page&#39;s current hash. We drop the first char from the returned hash as it is the hash (#) character itself. The hash value is essentially the location to be navigated to, hence, we use some string manipulation to craft a new URL from it, and make an AJAX request to fetch the contents of the page requested, and insert it into the div specified through Javascript.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	For example, suppose we are on about.html page. Now if I click &#39;contact&#39; link, the link would change to /about.html#/contact.html, the hash value would be grabbed by the window.location.hash method, a GET request is fired to get that location with a XMLHttpRequest object, the response is inserted with innerHTML method on the div, and using the &lt;code&gt;window.history.pushState()&lt;/code&gt; method, we update the URL to /contact.html, to ease sharing. All this, in the blink of an eye. Cool.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I could do it in two different ways. One was to just place the text in those files and inserting them into the template. The drawback of this was that if a user directly visits that page, he/she would just see plain text. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nagekar.com/assets/ajaxreload/&quot;&gt;check this link out&lt;/a&gt;. The Javascript code for that was,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/e53b6d308f3620e7b9a2.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The separate callback function for getHash was necessary because onclick() event fires before the hash is changed, and it would result in the script grabbing the previous hash. As already mentioned, the navigation is smooth if one visits index.html and then other links, but try getting the about.html page first. All you&#39;ll see are a few lines of text.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	A sloppy solution to the above problem was to replicate the entire index page with varying content for each of the page, and then replace entire DOM on anchor click. You can imagine this is not at all smart, and would destroy the point of this site. Not to mention the extra bandwidth to reload the same resources on every request. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nagekar.com/assets/ajaxreload2/&quot;&gt;Here is the implementation&lt;/a&gt; for this method.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	What would be the smarter way? Perhaps, making sure the first page to load always downloads the entire html every time, and subsequent requests to be made to download the changed content. I will be implementing this solution shortly. Drop in your ideas too, and share if you enjoyed reading this. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Edit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    So, the above code seemed to work on my localhost, but there were some serious (cross origins and some logical ones) issues with it, so much that I considered to learn relative and absolute links all over again. Anyways, I also happened to redesign my blog during this time (redesign in the sense changing the template), and I am working to implement AJAX loading on all links here on my blog. So far, all links on the home page seemed to work as expected (AJAXified). I am using the document.write() method, so judge me on that. You can check them out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nagekar.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The code snippet is following.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/abhn/330dcb193dd25e46607d.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    What do you think about it? It feels a little buggy at times, and sadly, Internet Explorer isn&#39;t supported yet. But for most of it, chrome and firefox are working like a charm. Hope to get all links covered under this thing, which would be nice. Sadly though, the browser tab shows loading for all the third party resources on the page which kill the purpose of this thing. Anyways, feel free to correct or improve this in the comments below.
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Exchanging Chikoos For Friends</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/01/exchanging-chikoos-for-friends.html"/>
   <updated>2016-01-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/01/exchanging-chikoos-for-friends</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
    Traveling to college everyday, in a train compartment, sitting on the same seat for about an hour, your entire attention is on your phone of course. Yes, it was surely enjoyable in the early days, but after a while, you don&#39;t get to see anything unusual most of the times. That is the reason if you ever spot me in a train compartment, I would be drowned into some book or my mobile phone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	It was a similar day today, morning 9 am. I was sitting by the window, enjoying the newest mix-tape I downloaded. I was into my phone screen when I noticed a &#39;Chikoo&#39; seller making his way through the boogie. I glanced at him through my peripheral sight and was soon back on the phone screen. I noticed the man sitting on the other side bought some 8 chickoo for Rs. 10, &lt;i&gt;&#39;Nice deal&#39;&lt;/i&gt;, I thought, &lt;i&gt;&#39;but cannot carry them to college&#39;&lt;/i&gt;. Just then, the man, who bought those Chikoos, started distributing those in between us, the people sitting next to him. I stared at him for a second, this time a bit carefully. He was a well groomed individual, in around his late 40s. He was the typical man you find in countryside India, and his preference for white outfit depicted that well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	He offered me chikoo, and I took it without any hesitations. It was real sweet. He gave away 7 of the 8 he had to the people around him, relished the one he had left in his hand, and started talking to the people, total strangers. He said that he didn&#39;t have a native place, and that makes him feel every place like his own. He chuckled. The people around him started with their stories and it was fun to hear. There were some five to six of them who were chatting like they were some long lost friends, when in fact, they had just met a few minutes ago. The smiles and the laughter I witnessed were something unforgettable. They spoke for sometime after that, while I, finding no room to add anything in those elderly talks, decided to put the music back on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	It did, however, teach me how important it is to give away, and how much joy it gives to the people who receive it. I learned that I need not have a bucket full of cash to bring a smile on someone&#39;s face. It can be done with some 10 bucks too. Plus what you get are some friends, who have a great first impression of yours in their minds. It is a small price to pay for those many returns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	It is funny how a random incident changes your point of views to that extent. People like these exist in our World, who call the World their home, and the people their very own. The World and Mother Nature are really our very own. It is just that we often forget it in our fast paced lives. Have a great time ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Private Local Cloud Storage Using Raspberrypi - How To</title>
   <link href="https://www.nagekar.com/2016/01/how-to-private-local-cloud-using-raspberrypi.html"/>
   <updated>2016-01-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://www.nagekar.com/2016/01/how-to-private-local-cloud-using-raspberrypi</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
	Today we&#39;ll see how you can home brew a cloud (in the local sense) storage solution that would be free to use, quite faster than an Internet based one, secure enough from any outside the network intrusion and customizable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	But why do you need to go to such lengths when you can easily create an account on Google and get 15 gigs of free storage. Well, first of all, data that we generate is increasing significantly each day. We have multiple devices with us, most of them with ~16-64 GB storage, which is not at all good enough. Then while our notebooks are getting faster with solid state drives, they are still costly to use for all of our needs like storing tonnes of movies and music videos, that is, if you are still left with space after cramming up your disk with camera pictures. If you opt for a premium account at Dropbox or Google Drive, it will easily cost you ~$100 a year recurring, the cost which can get you a 2 TB WD external hard disk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Then there is the speed issue. At least here in India, we are deprived Internet connection faster than 2-4 mbps. Most of the times even less than that. Even if we considered the option of backing to an online cloud storage, the bandwidth prevents us from efficiently using what already exists for free. When using an local cloud, the bandwidth is only throttled by your equipments, and most of the times you can easily get ~40-60 mbps, which is fine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The last issue, depending on how you see it, is the most and the least important. Security. If the files are going to be random movies and music videos, you might not be much worried about some hacker breaking into your cloud storage provider and downloading them, but on the other hand, if the files contain any kind of sensitive personally identifiable information, then you would worry. But having said that, I would always choose a secure storage solution from insecure ones if given an option, even if the data was not at all sensitive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Things you&#39;ll need&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Now that we&#39;ve discussed some merits and demerits, lets talk about building the thing. The things you&#39;ll need are,
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi (with all it&#39;s setup accessories), with Ethernet port&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Hard disk, any capacity, with SATA to USB converter&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Wireless router&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Ethernet cable or Wifi adapter&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;USB power hub [in some cases]&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setting up the hardware&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Connect the hard disk to the Raspberrypi&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Boot it up and login via ssh&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;i&gt;sudo fdisk -l&lt;/i&gt; and make sure the hard disk is shown. Note the device name (/dev/sdb or similar)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;If not, try usb power adapter&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;If it is showing, we&#39;ll have to make sure it mounts to the same location each time we boot up.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Create a folder for the mount point. I&#39;ll be using &lt;pre&gt;/var/www&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;It would be advisable to use a separate low privileged user for the process, since we will be changing the user home later on.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo chmod 775 /var/www&lt;/pre&gt; and &lt;pre&gt;sudo chown your_username /var/www&lt;/pre&gt; to set the permissions for reading, writing and executing.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo blkid&lt;/pre&gt; and note the uuid for the external hard disk. Copy it.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Now we need to make the mounting occur each time we boot the pi up. Open the fstab file by &lt;pre&gt;sudo nano /etc/fstab&lt;/pre&gt; and add the following line &lt;pre&gt;UUID=&quot;3b28d90f-8805-4ec4-978d-c53ee397a924&quot; /var/www ext4 defaults,errors=remount-ro 0 1&lt;/pre&gt; by editing the UUID, mount location and file system and keeping other things constant.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Reboot the pi, and your /var/www should now be pointing to the external hard disk. If so, you are done with this part of the tutorial. If not, check what did you miss. Also make sure you are able to read and write files to that directory from your user account. If not, recheck the steps, Google for solutions or comment for help.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setting up the FTP server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install vsftpd&lt;/pre&gt; to install the vsFTP server.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Open the vsftp configuration file by &lt;pre&gt;sudo nano /etc/vsftpd.conf&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;
			The would be a lot of options. Just go through and make sure the following lines are there and not commented. If not, add them.
&lt;pre&gt;
	anonymous_enable=NO
	local_enable=YES
	write_enable=YES
	chroot_local_user=YES
	force_dot_files=YES
	local_root=/var/www
	allow_writable_chroot=YES
&lt;/pre&gt;
		&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;After saving (Ctrl + x and then y) and exiting, restart vsftpd by &lt;pre&gt;sudo service vsftpd restart&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Lastly, change the user home to the FTP root, so that you&#39;ll directly get into the FTP server&#39;s root on logging into the FTP client. &lt;pre&gt;sudo usermod --home /var/www/ your_username&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	If all went well, we have a 100% working local cloud storage running off our pi. Now, since not everyone would like to login with terminal each time they wish to access the cloud, I make some customizations to make it easy for even my Mom and Dad to use the cloud.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	On the desktop, download and install filezilla. &lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install filezilla&lt;/pre&gt; should do it on deb derivatives. Create a launcher icon that triggers the command &lt;pre&gt;filezilla sftp://myUsername:myPassword@myIP:myPort/my/root&lt;/pre&gt; which in my case became &lt;pre&gt;filezilla sftp://abhishek:password@192.168.1.10:22/var/www&lt;/pre&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/desktop_icon.png&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot;/&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/filezillapi.png&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot;/&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	On the mobile phones (we have droids, three of us), I used the &#39;add ftp server&#39; option in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.estrongs.android.pop&amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ES File Explorer&lt;/a&gt; and created a shortcut on the home screen with the widgets menu. Hence, accessing the cloud was nothing more troublesome than accessing a local folder on the phone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/es1.png&quot; width=&quot;270&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/es2.png&quot; width=&quot;270&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/es3.png&quot; width=&quot;270&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Now I have my very own, secure, high speed cloud storage solution for all my devices and also for the family. It is really convenient and building a custom case for the thing, it looks pretty badass.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pisetup.jpg&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	What do you think?
&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
