<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Abhishek Nagekar&#39;s Blog</title>
 <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://www.nagekar.com"/>
 <updated>2015-11-03T20:37:27+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://www.nagekar.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Abhishek Nagekar</name>
   <email>abhishek@nagekar.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Passport Office</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/11/Passport-Office.html"/>
   <updated>2015-11-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/11/Passport-Office</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I had an appointment at the passport office for document verification at 10.30 in the morning. To be honest, I was worried, not because I had any problem in any of the documents, but because the thought of visiting a government office makes me nauseatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever visited a Government office, where you spent hours rushing from one counter to other, facing people at every stage who don&#39;t give the tiniest bit of importance to your existence, and you felt like you are in a totally different hostile country altogether? If yes, then you know exactly what I&#39;m talking about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today was something different. Although the reporting time was 10:30, I reached the place by 10, just in case. I was expecting hour long queues and chaos, but to my surprise, it was not that way. There was a queue, but there were hardly 10 people in it. After about 10 minutes of reaching, the security guard, who stood by the entry gate, called upon every one who had the reporting time of 10:30. He looked at our documents at a glance, did the physical security checks and we were in. It was still 10:20 on my watch. I went inside, where there were multiple counters. I stood in one of those. When my turn came, the lady at the counter took all my zeroxed documents and attached them to a file along with the application form. She gave me a form which had a token number on it. I was unsure about what to do next, but a helpful voice again called me and guided me towards the next room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next room was a large air conditioned hall, with a canteen, a zerox machine and many such convenience stuff. More importantly, it had three large LCD displays which displayed a table of token numbers and their corresponding counter locations. I sat there for around 10 minutes when I saw &quot;N150 - A7&quot; on the screen. I got up and went to the A7 counter. A lady there read all my documents and asked me to zerox a few more things. I did as she said. Then she captured my photograph, took my finger and thumb prints, and asked me to go ahead. All in all, the entire main hall and &#39;A&#39; section took 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, I was in a waiting room with other people, where there were the same monitors. Here I had to wait around 15 minutes before I saw &quot;N150 - B3&quot;. On this &#39;B&#39; counter, a lady verified every detail line by line, going through each minor issue. After this, she returned my documents and told me to wait for the third counter. I went into the same room as that earlier and waited for the next call. Somewhere around 15 minutes later, I saw &quot;N150 - C7&quot; on the screen. Here, I was greeted by a very pleasant man, who smiled as I entered. He looked at the documents, doing some typing at the same time. After about 30 seconds, he kept the folder, returned me my originals, and said, &quot;You&#39;re done here. Submit the token, and then you may leave&quot;. I smiled and gathered my originals, giving way to the next guy standing behind me. I checked my watch. It was 11:15. I returned the token slip, and went towards the exit. A very polite guard asked me to fill the feedback form, which had all sorts of questions. It should not be surprising that they deserved an &#39;excellent&#39; in almost all questions. I then left the premises, got into a rickshaw and went home, with a totally changed mindset for Government offices. Oh boy, I wish all government offices were like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summarizing my experiences, the entire process was smooth as silk. It was because of the excellent management of the people who worked there. They deserve the entire credits. Not a single person looked like he/she was forced to work there, something you often see in such places (My personal experience with SBI bank). Everyone made me feel good, and my work important. I was treated nicely, even though I didn&#39;t get down from a VIP car at their premises, or had a call from a bureaucrat beforehand. The entire process was way better then what I could have ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, a big thank you on behalf of me and the thousands others who visit these Passport Seva Kendra all over the nation with dreams in their minds. While I was sitting in the initial hall, I noticed a quote from Mahatma Gandhi, that hung down a large poster. I couldn&#39;t photograph it since it was prohibited, but this was the exact quote. I am happy that they didn&#39;t just put it, but were following it on every step. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/customer-service.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Image source: http://blog.freshdesk.com/being-dependent-is-good-reminder-on-independence-day/&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CSS Crash Course</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/10/CSS-Crash-Course.html"/>
   <updated>2015-10-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/10/CSS-Crash-Course</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a friend, who happens to be a good C and assembly programmer, but simply hates anything related to web, then be it HTML, CSS or anything way too much abstracted for that matter. Since it was compulsory for us to make our own web application project for college, he struggled to learn it (CSS and HTML) from here and there, cursing it at the same time. Hence this little guide, for all those of you who hate it, but still want to get your work done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A thing or two about CSS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSS isn&#39;t a markup language. It is a styling language, and hence, it won&#39;t really work if you have no document in the first place. Creating a document simply means adding some data to HTML tags in a web page. Here onwards, document would mean the HTML page that we are working on. Let us create one as an example.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;code&gt;
  &amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Testing&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Awesome Site&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;A little heading&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A paragraph containing some text&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Some information&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;More text...&amp;lt;/&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very basic example that would display something like the following. You can guess what each tag stands for here, if not, &#39;h&#39; tag stands for heading, &#39;h1&#39; being the largest to &#39;h6&#39; being the smallest. &#39;p&#39; stands for paragraph, and there are many &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3schools.com/html/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;such tags&lt;/a&gt;, which are used as and when required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/css_files/test1.html&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it is time to style our document. I will place all the CSS styling in a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag, which I will be placing into the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; of the document. Now you must know that I could do the exact same thing by using an external CSS file and linking it, or by styling individual elements using inline CSS. We will see what those are later. I think the main heading should be red, the subordinate headings should be green and the paragraphs should be orange. I also think the background should be a little off white. Let&#39;s see how that translates into CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
 body {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;background-color: #eee;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  h1 {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: red;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  h3 {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: green;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  p {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: orange;&lt;br/&gt;
  }
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have styled our page, let&#39;s take another look at it.&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/css_files/test2.html&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like it works, although it is looking ugly. Anyways, what we have used here is the &lt;i&gt;element selector&lt;/i&gt; of CSS which, not surprisingly, selects the elements matching the tag name and applies the properties defined for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;ID and Class selectors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there may be times when you have multiple elements with same tag names but you want to apply CSS properties to only specific element(s). That is where the &#39;id&#39; and the &#39;class&#39; selector comes in. Note that however, the class here does now refer to anything from your object oriented programming books. It only gives those elements with that class a particular grouping. You can use any one of &#39;id&#39; and &#39;class&#39; as per your liking for now, but conventionally, we use &#39;id&#39; for uniquely identifying elements and &#39;class&#39; for grouping similar elements. Technically, there is an additional difference of precedence here, with the &#39;id&#39; having more precedence than &#39;class&#39;. My personal rule is that, for custom CSS use &#39;id&#39;, since frameworks like Bootstrap (which we will check out later on) usually use &#39;class&#39;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we shall rewrite the document adding an id attribute to each tag name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;code&gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;h1 id=&amp;quot;logo&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Awesome Site&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;h3 id=&amp;quot;heading&amp;quot;&amp;gt;A little heading&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p id=&amp;quot;content&amp;quot;&amp;gt;A paragraph containing some text&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;h3 id=&amp;quot;other-heading&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Some information&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p id=&amp;quot;other-content&amp;quot;&amp;gt;More text...&amp;lt;/&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and we shall change the CSS accordingly&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;code&gt;
  #logo {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: red;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #heading {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: green;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #other-heading {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: olive;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #content {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: orange;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #other-content {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: purple;&lt;br/&gt;
  }
&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting page looks something like this, with each of the individual elements appearing in different color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/css_files/test3.html&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we could have well written &#39;class&#39; instead of &#39;id&#39; in our document, but then instead of &lt;code&gt;#logo&lt;/code&gt; it would have been &lt;code&gt;.class&lt;/code&gt;, which is the class selector. Having learnt two selectors, we can now combine them to get the desired result. For example, &lt;code&gt;h3#heading { color: blue; }&lt;/code&gt; would turn &lt;span style=&quot;color: blue;&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt; all the h3 tags that have a &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;id=&quot;heading&quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; attribute declared. Similarly, &lt;code&gt;h3.heading { color: blue; }&lt;/code&gt; would result in the same thing to all the h3 tags with &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;class=&quot;heading&quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Group selectors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group selectors are used to apply properties to multiple elements at once. Multiple elements are separated by commas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;code&gt;
  #logo {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: red;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #heading {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: green;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #other-heading {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: olive;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #content {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: orange;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  #other-content {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;color: purple;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
  /* Selecting all three tag names at once. */&lt;br/&gt;
  h1, h3, p {&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;background-color: yellow;&lt;br/&gt;
  }&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which will look like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/css_files/test4.html&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Descendant selectors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, CSS properties needs to be applied only to tags within a specific tag or id. In such situations, the descendant selector comes in handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;code&gt;
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Testing&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;ul em {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;font-size: 1.25em;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Look what I&amp;apos;ve &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;got for ya!&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;item 1&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;item 2&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;item 3&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;this looks abnormal&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;item 5&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this will render&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/css_files/test5.html&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look how the &lt;em&gt;emphasis&lt;/em&gt; at the top is normal but the one in the &#39;ul&#39; is enlarged. There is another similar selector called the child selector. It works similar to descendant selector but demands the child to be DIRECT descendant of the parent. For example, &lt;code&gt;p &gt; a { color: green; }&lt;/code&gt; will cause only the anchors directly children to any paragraph to look &lt;span style=&quot;color: green;&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt;. These are the various selectors that you would see and probably use when dealing with web applications. Simple enough, aren&#39;t they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although div and span are html tags, any modern web application that you will write will heavily make use of these to group sections of the web page together. You might be familiar with the layouts of most websites these days, with a header on top, one or two column in the center with content and other options, and a footer at the bottom. Even on my blog, you&#39;ll notice these three things. How are they made, and how to make them look so distinct that on the first glance, your visitors know what their purpose is. The answer lies in making proper divs and adding appropriate CSS to it. Div is a block element, which means that it is used to style multiple elements at once. Span, on the other hand, is inline, that is, it is used to style little chunks of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will write the 4 sections of a website I mentioned earlier, using divs. Read the code and you would understand what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;code&gt;

&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Testing&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;* {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;text-align: center; &lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;#header {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;background-color: red;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;height: 50px;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;#container {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;width: auto;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;margin: 0 auto;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;#body {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;width: 75%;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;float: left;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;background-color: grey;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;#side {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;width: 25%;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;float: right;&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;background-color: blue;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;#footer {&lt;br/&gt;
      &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;background-color: green;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;header&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Header Text&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;container&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;body&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Content goes here&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
    &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;side&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Sidebar&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;footer&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Copyrights&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sure looks beautiful, doesn&#39;t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/css_files/test6.html&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This completes the CSS syntax part. I did mention that you can write all your CSS in a file.css and include them in your document head with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;link href=&quot;/assets/style.css&quot; rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so that it is easier to maintain the code. There is yet another way to add CSS, which makes use of @import syntax. It is better avoided for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/10036977/best-way-to-include-css-why-use-import&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;linked reasons&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;p&gt;Now that you are well equipped with the necessary things to learn some actual and practical CSS, you must be really excited to read from w3schools. It is a great site to begin, and since it comes on top each time you search for anything related to CSS (or web programming, for that matter), you may use it as your sole reference guide. Nothing bad, but keep in mind that after leaving your nutshell, you should &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3fools.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;avoid that site&lt;/a&gt;, and start using some reputed docs instead, like the ones from &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mozilla&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;CSS Frameworks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speed up the development process, you might want to check out some libraries out there that would ease your life. One of the best is &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;. It would enable you to do rapid development, with minimal typing. Bootstrap comes with jQuery, a Javascript library which also helps a lot dealing with web application stuff you are about to deal with. There is not much point reading the official docs if you only want to get the work done. Instead, I would suggest you to Google out things, pick up code on the way, keep going. That is exactly how I used to do stuff back then, when I hated to write CSS and HTML. Bad advice, but gets the job done most of the times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Outro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CSS is amazing. Web is amazing. Today is a time when you either have to love the web, or keep fighting a losing battle convincing yourself that you don&#39;t need it. Either way, knowing a thing or two about how the web pages that you spend more than half of your time on, are styled, is always a plus. As always, for anything, the comment box is always there. Corrections, please. Liked the article? Suggest it to your friends! Thank you for reading.&lt;p&gt;







</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Birthday Week</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/09/Birthday-Week.html"/>
   <updated>2015-09-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/09/Birthday-Week</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here it comes, finally, my birthday. Not that it is something new this time, but surely one of the special ones because I passed another decade here on Earth. Last time this happened, I didn&#39;t realize how important it was, maybe because I was just 10 back then. But this time, it would be different. I realized I have moved around the Sun 20 times now, which is amazing, because I have travelled around 18.8 trillion kilometers, since my birth, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earth%27s_orbit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;relative to the sun&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That is a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 3rd of October this year, I will have lived some 7305 days which comes to about 613 million seconds. Woah! Good going. I travel a lot, and almost all of it is from and to my college. My college is 61 kilometers from home, and I am into it for the last 2 and a half years. Considering a usual semester to be of 3 months (which is lower bound for most semesters) and a usual month to have 22 working days, in the last 5 semesters I have travelled around 40,260 kilometers; a little more than the circumference of the earth at the equator. I wish I had had the fortune to visit another country or even distant parts of my own, but that&#39;s all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20 years is a lot of time. From a pilot, to astronaut, to a star gazer and now a computer guy who talks code and science. My ambitions never ceased to motivate me. There have been some really nice moments, like getting into an engineering college, getting a personal computer and a mobile phone, good friends who love food and all. I was fortunate enough to be born in a family where I get all that I needed, to do things that I love, because what I am looking at is 20% of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poverty_in_India&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;poverty in India&lt;/a&gt;; people who earn less than INR26 a day. Life has been really good, somehow. Hopefully I use it to the fullest, make some contribution to this world, earn money so that I can buy all those things I had wished for. Earn respect, value and more. I am a strong believer in Steve Job&#39;s &quot;Your time is limited, so don&#39;t waste it living someone else&#39;s dream&quot; quote. Our lives are too short for anything but these little materialistic dreams. Dreams in which we grow to be some mainstream professionals, to help people do their thing, which in turn earn us money which we use to do our thing, occasionally become millionares, buy fast cars and live in nice apartments, die. Some may not even see the Halley&#39;s comet in their lives, which is for me, something real. Whatever we have, is right here, right now. Future cannot be predicted, nor can past be changed. However, we still have our present in our hands. What we do with it is subjective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I am sharing my birthday with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fsf.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Free Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt; and GNU project. They have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/gnu30/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;turned 30&lt;/a&gt; this year, which is cool. RMS would be real proud at where his initiative has reached today. I would like all of the people reading this to hit the link once and read about GNU and it&#39;s philosophy. I feel they are amazing people, and their contributions to the community, especially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gnu.org/gnu30&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://static.fsf.org/nosvn/misc/GNU_30th_badge.png&quot; alt=&quot;[ Celebrate 30 years of GNU! ]&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>You Are Insignificant</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/09/You-Are-Insignificant.html"/>
   <updated>2015-09-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/09/You-Are-Insignificant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to write at this point, so much that I am not even sure where to start. Humans are such wonderful creatures, we make things happen, world spin, or at least believe it to be that way. We have a self-imagined feeling of superiority. We are desperate to feel important, to feel blessed, to feel we have some purpose in life, and no one has to right to point at the way you walk on the face of this planet. We humans are so vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life goes up and down all the time, with just about everyone. We all have bad times, spend some days talking about it, and then everything gets back to normal. Now the interesting part comes when you have a logical mind. I judge myself and the decisions I take. It just turned out, when you&#39;re sad, it is not that the day is a little too gloomy, or that the trees are all looking down, or that the world is a little too quite. It is just that you&#39;re sad. That&#39;s it. Done. No one, other that your little brain in there, feels a damn thing. The world is a pretty large place. The Universe, a little larger. You, me, we are too small. No one cares about you, or your thoughts, let alone the Universe as a whole. You only matter if you can make money, and that is very temporary, only applicable on earth. So basically, you are worth a rock floating in space, even less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see people crying over little things, things so little that it almost feels a shame to cry over. You can&#39;t ask people to live according to you, of course not. What you can really ask is to show a little respect to the 3.5 billion years of evolution, that they are at the front of right now. Life wasn&#39;t easy. From the hot geysers, to the half dozen catastrophic disasters that shock everything on our little planet. Life made it through them, and for every specie that you see today, at least 1000 have perished, and then you tell me that this guy is trying to ignore you and you are feeling left out. Come on people, don&#39;t be that weak. We are a race that has been here from quite some time. The end might be near somewhere, in the next 100 or 1000 years, if we stop thinking about our individual existence and our special place in this Universe we might make it out to a few thousand years. And unless we move to some other world before that, there is not much probability that we can save us from ourselves. World would completely reset itself, and your current values would be deep buried inside some fossils down the surface. The sun would expand into a red super giant and eat up the earth&#39;s atmosphere. Our galaxy Milky Way would collide with it&#39;s sister galaxy Andromeda. Artistic fiery show of stars and nebulas it would be, for some other civilization far way just opening their eyes to the Universe. The sun would soon die, and there would only be darkness after that, for eternity. No one, yes, NO ONE, would ever know how much you struggled when you existed for those 60 years in that entire 11 billion years of solar system&#39;s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So shall we begin the discussion about your life&#39;s struggles now?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Need For An Alternate Social Network</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/08/Need-For-An-Alternate-Social-Network.html"/>
   <updated>2015-08-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/08/Need-For-An-Alternate-Social-Network</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About a week or so ago, we were asked to choose our &#39;web-technologies&#39; project, that would be among a group of two or three, and to be completed within the course of the semester. After forming team with two of my buddies at the college, we started to discuss about the possible theme of the project. From the very beginning, I had this idea to create a social network. After discussing with the other two, or I would rather say after convincing them, we finally settled to create a &#39;social network&#39; model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can call me an avid social networker. I spend most of my free time staring at my computer&#39;s screen and most of the times, I am not actually working but surfing the social networks I have unnecessarily signed up with, which eat up most of my productive time. Well, at least that was the truth up to a few months ago. I have made some interesting, and more appropriately, disturbing observations about most of the people on these social networks. Social networks are not the online social places anymore. They have become more anti-social networks. How?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, when was the last time you saw an ugly or not-so-perfect photo of your friend on Facebook? Or when was it that you read his or her tweet that didn&#39;t have that touch of wit in it? Hard to remember, isn&#39;t it? Not all do it, but one thing you might admit, most do. We hate to feel inferior. We want ourselves to be perceived better than the rest, and in that struggle to keep our fake identity updated, we keep adding tiny bits of false facts to that image. We have image editing and filter apps more than ever. Sites that provide humorous one liners are now full time. There is a rivalry to stay on top of the popularity ladder. People consider themselves less of a user, and more of a brand. Everyone wants to have an identity online, start a vogue, get famous, all in the easiest possible way. Who want to take the effort to create or discover something? Scientists are fools. Better is to use what you got at your disposal. Make stupid statements about others to get those 5 seconds of fame. Expose your body to get followers, is what exactly happens on Instagram half of the times. Click-bait headlines are all over the place, no site to trust over it&#39;s content. News websites have started to look more like link exchange sites. The Internet is not the same good old place to share thoughts anymore, but a shameless self-promotion hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what might be the possible solution to this? First culprit, in my opinion, is the followers thing. The problem lies in inequality in the distribution of followers. Some famous people get more followers, and in turn, get more &#39;likes&#39; and &#39;retweets&#39; even on their lamest posts. On the other hand, if some random guy posts a very interesting research, he doesn&#39;t have the audience, so maybe his research won&#39;t get that far. Now maybe he won&#39;t mind it this time, but in the long run, when he and countless others like him, don&#39;t get the appreciation they deserve but see crappy content making it to the trending news, maybe they will stop their research and get into making the content that makes it to the top. From experience, we know what content actually does. This is exactly how we are discouraging quality content on the Internet. Some sites have kept up very well (see Reddit) but for most, the future doesn&#39;t look as good. The only apparent solution to this is to keep the &#39;followers&#39; thing for topics, and not for people. That way, a celebrity and a commoner gets equal chance to be heard, and hence, reach out to the millions of other users typically found on any average sized social network today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing concerns me more, because it is not about the technology, but about the users of it. We are raising a generation which will never know the joy of meeting friends after a while, the joy of hanging out together and the joy in laughing over yourself. Because today fun is what is made of the poor and the powerless, and laughter is what you have when someone gets hurt. News is what the celebrities are up to, and sports is what the richest guys bet. The world has more of everything than ever, still life is more monotonos than ever. Let&#39;s be honest, how many birthdays would you actually remember if there had been no reminders on Facebook? Not many, but still we go to the extent of doing a formality of typing &#39;hbd&#39; on our friend&#39;s wall on his or her birthday. Interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The online social universe is degrading each day, and we are not doing much to help it. Good sources of news and content are like one in a thousand, if not less. The things must be changed, or it may not be long before Internet loses it&#39;s meaning, and not stay worthy of spending time on, much like the television these days.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>4th Semester And Then</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/08/4th-sem-exams-and-later.html"/>
   <updated>2015-08-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/08/4th-sem-exams-and-later</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It was in June that I appeared for my 4th semester exam (we have 8 in all, 2 each year). That makes me one half of an engineer, as far as the certification thing is concerned. Apart from that, I would not consider myself anywhere near to what standards I have for an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nagekar.com/2015/03/engineering.html&quot;&gt;Engineer&lt;/a&gt; in my mind. Nevertheless, the results were displayed late last month, and I managed to clear all the subjects, proudly entering the 3rd year of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since the exams, I did a few interesting things that I would like to let you know. Just after the exams, I took to &lt;a href=&quot;http://qt.io/&quot;&gt;Qt framework&lt;/a&gt; in C++ which I did for the next one month or so. Not much, but I did the QWidget class well enough to have coded some &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/abhn/Data-Destroyer-GUI&quot;&gt;simple GUIs&lt;/a&gt;. It was quite interesting, and a useful asset that I think I own now. Later the interest turned towards web [again! :]. I started working on a social network written in Python, Django. I will update you once I get the base ready, and since it is the largest of all the projects I have worked on, I am quite proud and happy for it. Lastly, something even more amazing happened. I found my lost interest in Physics and Astronomy back. It is quite interesting, as to how it happened, but I will save that for a separate post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past two months have been great, from my personal perspective. I have basically transformed into someone else, hopefully wiser than I was before. Hopefully. There is a strong reasoning I found for making that statement. I started reading a lot, doubting even more and I found that it opened doors to newer dimensions to living my life. Everything, everyone exists just because they do. That&#39;s it. Nobody, nothing, especially the universe, owes you an explanation to things that seem incomprehensible. Learn to accept it. Maybe it is a part of growing up, which I seem to have realized now. For what it&#39;s worth, I will still stay curious, for that is what drives me and most of the people. Good night.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Social Share Counts Python Implementation</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/Social-Share-Counts-Python-Implementation.html"/>
   <updated>2015-07-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/Social-Share-Counts-Python-Implementation</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this little script that grabs the count of shares on popular social networks, using their APIs. I have listed the documentation on the project page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/abhn/Social-Share-Counts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. I will copy the relevant pieces of readme here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-network-apis&quot;&gt;Social Network APIs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;https://graph.facebook.com/?id=https://www.github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response:
&lt;code&gt;json
{
   &quot;id&quot;: &quot;http://www.github.com&quot;,
   &quot;shares&quot;: 31684
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;http://cdn.api.twitter.com/1/urls/count.json?url=https://github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response:
&lt;code&gt;json
{&quot;count&quot;:14,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;http:\/\/github.com\/&quot;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;google-plus&quot;&gt;Google Plus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;https://plusone.google.com/_/+1/fastbutton?url=https://github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This returns the +1 button. I extracted the counts using regex &lt;code&gt;window.__SSR = {c: ([\d]+)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linkedin&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;http://www.linkedin.com/countserv/count/share?url=https://github.com&amp;amp;format=json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response:
&lt;code&gt;json
{&quot;count&quot;:0,&quot;fCnt&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;fCntPlusOne&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https:\/\/github.com&quot;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stumbleupon&quot;&gt;StumbleUpon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;http://www.stumbleupon.com/services/1.01/badge.getinfo?url=https://github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response too large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pinterest&quot;&gt;Pinterest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;http://api.pinterest.com/v1/urls/count.json?url=https://github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response:
&lt;code&gt;json
receiveCount({&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com&quot;,&quot;count&quot;:0}) 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reddit&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;http://www.reddit.com/api/info.json?url=https://github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This returns a lot of data, which can be easily used to extracted counts. 
&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; that the Reddit guys don’t really like automated requests and may cause the call to return HTTP 429.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vkontakte&quot;&gt;Vkontakte&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Request:
&lt;code&gt;https://vk.com/share.php?act=count&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;url=https://github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response:
&lt;code&gt;json
VK.Share.count(1, 419);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marks the end of the documentation. I hope that serves some purpose. The reason I wrote this was that I wanted social sharing buttons on this blog. I could not afford any of the mainstream buttons like Addthis and Sharethis. They kill the load time, and I’m already struggling with Disqus and Adsense overload. More on that soon. I hope to create a ‘dynamic looking’ static set of buttons for this blog, and I’ll update you if I get time to complete it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>First Anniversary Of My Blog</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/First-Anniversary-Of-My-Blog.html"/>
   <updated>2015-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/First-Anniversary-Of-My-Blog</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month, I was reminded by Bigrock.in about the pending renewal of nagekar.com. It was through an email. I had completely forgotten the date of registering the site and it came in as a handy reminder. 6&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of June it was, in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an affinity towards blogs and blogging right from when I was 15. That was when I had seen the first blogs and shortly after that, it was when I created my first blog. It was in the morning, of 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; March, 2011. I knew I was up to something awesome. 7 in the morning, I was home alone. I remember mom and dad had to go out early, to receive some guests. I spent an effort filled three hours and finally got the site up at around 10 am. The domain was &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekystuffforall.webs.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;geekystuffforall.webs.com&lt;/a&gt; (It reads, Geeky Stuff For All, if you had trouble). It felt good, to have an identity. I wrote a paragraph for the homepage, which was the first post for me, ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, if you are searching for someone who thinks spending 8 hours in front of a PC is normal, you are at the right place ;)&lt;br&gt;You will not find any amazing new hacks or such stuff here.Then why this site ? It is because I am not a computer expert but computer enthusiast just like you. I will try to share whatever new I come to know. I would be extremely pleased to hear from you.&lt;br&gt;By the way I am Abhishek Nagekar. You can meet me on Facebook(If you like to !!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;March 5, 2011&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that was also the last thing I wrote on that blog. It was not that I got bored or anything, but I was quick to realize more amazing platforms are available that gave more control to bloggers. I created something called cyber-outlaws.blogspot.com to post all the tricks and hacks I then knew. I worked pretty well. I had around 800 views in the first month, which is good number compared to even this blog. Then came many more blogs on numberous subdomains on almost every popular free hosting out there. My &#39;niche&#39; had changed from hacks and tricks to mobiles and gadgets, news and reviews alike. I though about moving on from something.somehost.com to something.com, mostly because of the fact that I could have a custom@something.com like email address. I registered my first top level domain, lulztec.com on Godaddy. It costed about INR 99, or USD 2, under a promo scheme. It was back in May or June, 2013. I was just out of junior college, and it was time to make some money. I blogged and blogged, but did not get the traffic I was expecting. After 2 or 3 failed attempts to signup for Google Adsense, I finally settled for Chitika and Infolinks. I didn&#39;t make anything for the next 6 months I kept them on my site (I did actually make $2.80, but I will call it nothing because the cashout was $100, so I never actually got anything in hand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought there was more to blogging than just posting new stuff everyday. I moved everything to a paid hosting company called Visiba. They were charging around $2/month back then. I was really impressed by their service and kept my blog there for another three months. Later, not seeing any improvements, I had to think what next to do, that would work. I purchased a small VPS from DigitalOcean, where I moved the blog and started writing Linux tutorials. I was paying $5/month to DigitalOcean, which is considered low for a VPS. Still, there was no sign of revenue and I was spending a great deal of time on blogging. I knew I had to change things. I registered a new domain called tutshub.net, where I decided to post technical tutorials. It worked only a little better with this one. Meanwhile,  I was accompanied by my school friend, who used to be a blogger too. Together, we managed to get our blog under alexa 400k which was cool, I thought. Also, we tried our hands in the web development world, and registered nakshtra.org, which failed miserably. Tutshub.net was going good and it was mostly because of my partner Harshal, who worked harder than me. Here&#39;s a snapshot I found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140403181109/http://www.tutshub.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/w7javylj8drmulm/tutshub.net.png?raw=1&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we decided to stop that blog. The last post was made in February 2014, and then we orphaned it. Blogging helped me to realize there is much more I can do, than just write about other people&#39;s achievements. I got to be better than that, I thought. I still don&#39;t know if it was a good decision but it definitely helped me concentrate on myself. It was a few months later, in June, that I got this blog. It was not aimed to be a traffic scoring blog, because I know for sure now, I cannot blog for traffic. One year passed, 30 articles written, tried many new languages and frameworks, got accepted by Adsense, did average in academics, made some great friends in college and many great things happened in just this year. I am glad I decided to start this blog which, as I have always said, is a diary to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happened, many people have appreciated the things I write, and there have been a lot of feedbacks, positive and constructive alike. I share this one year with you&#39;ll, who took the time to read my thoughts. The past is history, quite a beautiful one. You, me, we grew wiser each day, and we&#39;ve no intention of changing that. Finally, happy birthday! to my blog. Here&#39;s to more good content in future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Blog Moved To Github</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/blog-moved-to-github.html"/>
   <updated>2015-07-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/blog-moved-to-github</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Take a look around. Everything&#39;s changed. Yet again. I am sure you&#39;re probably sick of me changing the total appearance of this blog every 3 months or so, and you&#39;re right in being so. Let&#39;s go back into a little history. Around a year from now, I stumbled across &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Ghost blogging platform&lt;/a&gt;. It was clean, neat and beautiful. I knew I always wanted something like that to write. I didn&#39;t have this &lt;i&gt;(nagekar.com)&lt;/i&gt; domain at that time. I went ahead and started their trial, which gave me a subdomain at &lt;i&gt;ghost.io&lt;/i&gt; to blog on. It was beautiful, visually and the overall experience. After having dealth with most of the popular opensource PHP content management systems like Wordpress, Joomla and Drupal, this was something new altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I registered this domain, about a week later and started using their minimal plan of $5 per month, which included 10k pageviews. It took me not long to realize that I couldn&#39;t afford those $5 because, 1) it was a personal blog from which I wasn&#39;t making any revenue, and 2) because being a student, I have to save money to utilize in other areas like books and all. I got off there, with the half dozen articles I published while I was there for a month and a half. I, with those articles in my backpack started wondering like a hunter, looking for a new shelter, cheap and simple. &lt;a href=&quot;https://svbtle.com/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Svbtle&lt;/a&gt; was another platform that I liked, unfortunately I didn&#39;t have an invite at that time, and even when I got the invite, the custom domain feature, which I needed, was only available to paid customers. Of course not everything can be free, and I have no complaints, rather I am grateful to them for such a wonderful platform. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nagekar.com/2014/07/ghost-vs-blogger-view.html&quot;&gt;I had to settle for Blogger&lt;/a&gt;, as the forced ads in Wordpress were something that made me hate Wordpress.com. Initially, with a custom theme, a little complicated, but later reverted to simple one. Then I went to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/creating-custom-blogger-template-from.html&quot;&gt;code my own&lt;/a&gt;, which turned out to be successful, as far as my goal was concerned. It was perfect. No foreign code and nothing that increased the load time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a problem with near perfect things. They are boring. And so, I thought, was my blog. No new problems to troubleshoot and no commandline to work with. Blogger is everything what a writer sometimes needs, but we computer people are a different breed. We need problems, then be it in our own personal blogs. While randomly surfing, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a blog-like platform created to be used with Github, to publish static pages. I knew not much about how Ruby applications are, or how to set one, but thanks to their excellent documentation, I was able to set it up in less than a day. There is no database, simple text files which become posts and pages. Github automatically parses markup or markdown in the post, and you have a nice little blog which is free, easy to manage and test locally, everyone can see the source, plus new stuff can be published with a mere git push.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the way the blog looks and feels. It is important for me to like it since I mostly blog for selfish reasons, haha, but I hope it is comfortable for others to navigate too. I would like to hear anything regarding the new look of my blog down in the comments, and constructive suggestions are welcome. Keep visiting.&lt;p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Love For Graphical User Interface</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/love-for-graphical-user-interface.html"/>
   <updated>2015-07-03T20:38:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/07/love-for-graphical-user-interface</id>
   <content type="html">I considered myself a &#39;programmer&#39;. One who can make stuff happen, put it on paper, my thoughts and use it as a framework to create working stuff in the digital world. As any programmer, I learnt to write command line programs first. What are command line programs, you&#39;d ask. Well, a Command Line Interface (CLI) is an interface which reacts to not visual, but textual inputs from the keyboard. You never need a mouse to work with a command line, of course, if you&#39;re skilled with that particular type.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Command lines were the only way people worked with computers in the past. It was a time when the other name for people who worked with computers was programmers and hackers. No one else had the time or skill to learn and master the complicated systems. But like everything, it changed. Back in 1973, we had the first computer system that ran a GUI, or Graphical User Interface. As it sounds, yes everything was now controlled by pointing device, better known to us as a mouse. This was the onset of computers for the non programmers. Now, everyone could learn how to make computers do stuff with few &#39;clicks&#39;. We never actually looked back since.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But same was not true for people who program the computer. Programmers still and will always prefer the command line interface for most simple tasks. There are actually some tough reasons for this statement. Mainly, although the task to master CLI tools is not easy, once you do it, it feels much more comfortable than to use the every changing GUI. Not to mention the low resources that are required to run these utilities, and consistency over different platforms or operating systems. As an example, I can write a CLI tool in Python and C++ to run on Windows and Linux, and you won&#39;t be able to spot the difference between the four instances. Can I do the same with GUIs? No, at least not right now.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For the above few reasons, I never gave a thought to learning GUI programming, in any language. You don&#39;t want to do something that is of no use to you, right? Maybe.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After been coding for sometime now, I gave a thought to why some people who are not very good programmers, succeed more than people who are great programmers. It was a thing that deserved a thought. After reading several success and failure stories on Medium and Quora, I was convinced that there is no lack of skill in any field on this planet. Take anything for example, like I thought about C++. The language I am getting better at everyday, people have been learning it from the past 30 years. Who am I challenging? It struck me that mastering some form of art (yes, programming is as much an art for me as astronomy) and creating something that people use, are not necessarily same sets. Though there is a large area of intersection, you can&#39;t be sure that just being good at something will make you successful, whatever that word means here. It was good time for me to stop thinking about how good of a shot I am at programming, and start focusing on what the world actually needs that I can provide or produce, if at all I can.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That was the time I realized, CLIs are great, but if you want everyone to use your thing, you need to give them something they will love. You need to help them in a way that they are able to use the help. How did I expect everyone to love the CLI just because I think it is cool and looks all black and white (well, that&#39;s what I think is cool).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not everyone is a nerd. Not everyone has to be one. The world is so diverse. It is really satisfying to see an artist painting, a drummer performing and an athlete giving his best. It is this diversity, in us, the animals and the plants as well that makes our home, the Earth. We, geeks and nerds are no different. We love making stuff that work to our command. But we, like every other human present, also has the morale duty to help others with the stuff that excites us. Just as a painter sells his paintings, not only because he wants to earn from it, but also because he wants his art to spread, so that somewhere in a living room of some house, the hosts always get asked, &#39;where did you get this masterpiece from?&#39;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is a very different joy in seeing your creation being used. It is something different than doing what you love. Yes, it really is different. It brings the best out of you, a kind of motivation. I wanted to make something like that. I wanted to write GUIs. I took up learning it about a month ago, and I am kind of comfortable with Qt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are a lot of frameworks for writing GUIs, as anybody using a computer today can imagine. Plus, many high level languages provide APIs to write graphical applications within the language libraries, Java for instance. Still, having done some programming in C++, I had two basic options open in front of me, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikivs.com/wiki/GTK_vs_Qt&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GTK+ and Qt&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/129355/what-is-difference-between-gtk-and-qt-applications&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I choose Qt&lt;/a&gt; after reading some &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9441127/gui-development-qt-vs-gtk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;articles on Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; from users with similar dilemma. Qt is cool, lots of possibilities and support. Code is quite portable, and an important thing, I am enjoying it, which matters a lot, right?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;If you wonder where am I right now with it, I am writing a GUI wrapper for the GNU&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dd_%28Unix%29&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dd utility&lt;/a&gt; which should make it simple for someone who&#39;s just started using GNU/Linux to burn ISOs to disks, without the hassle of setting up a more than required complex tool or destroying the data trying to use dd from the command line by messing up the &#39;if&#39; and &#39;of&#39;, for example.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-sppW3p-8Aug/VZacFriakLI/AAAAAAAAH_E/LTauqZAYW2E/s1600/Screenshot%2B-%2BFriday%2B03%2BJuly%2B2015%2B-%2B07%253A57%253A13%2B%2BIST.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;282&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-sppW3p-8Aug/VZacFriakLI/AAAAAAAAH_E/LTauqZAYW2E/s320/Screenshot%2B-%2BFriday%2B03%2BJuly%2B2015%2B-%2B07%253A57%253A13%2B%2BIST.png&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;Neat, huh? Haha. I will put it up once I finish it, but the important thing is, I could do it. The best part about being a programmer is, adapting is too easy. At least when beginning. And that is mandatory, given the ever changing world of Information Technology.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;I&#39;ll conclude this long post here. If you made it till here, then a big thank you. I feel it is hard to read what I write, because I tend to write my feeling, and mostly they don&#39;t look the same on paper. Nevertheless, do tell me what you think about this article. Liked it, hated it, anything.&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Creating Custom Blogger Template From Scratch</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/creating-custom-blogger-template-from.html"/>
   <updated>2015-06-15T20:21:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/creating-custom-blogger-template-from</id>
   <content type="html">Although when I started with it, I hardly knew anything about a blogger template, but it turned out, designing a blogger template is easier than designing a HTML template. Just a few basic concepts and you are good to go.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Firstly, before digging into the template code, we will look at the grammar needed to code our thing. This simple article assumes you can read basic HMTL, CSS and XML. Nothing above the basic level, plain simple stuff. If not, whenever you do not understand something, make sure you search that term or tag on &lt;a href=&quot;http://w3schools.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;w3schools&lt;/a&gt; to understand it. Yes, that&#39;s all you really need, trust me.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Planning the layout&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;br /&gt;First of all, how do you want your blog to look like when it&#39;s done. Just a basic idea would do. You must know what you are working for. Here is what I made. It is the way most simple blogs look like. Two column layout, a header on top and a footer at bottom.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#999;} .tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#999;color:#444;background-color:#F7FDFA;} .tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#999;color:#fff;background-color:#26ADE4;} .tg .tg-vpsr{font-size:26px;text-align:center} .tg .tg-szh5{font-size:26px} .tg .tg-n27c{font-size:26px;background-color:#bbdaff;color:#343434;text-align:center} &lt;/style&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;tg&quot;&gt;  &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;    &lt;th class=&quot;tg-vpsr&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Header&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;tg-szh5&quot;&gt;Blog Posts                        &lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;tg-szh5&quot;&gt;Sidebar&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;tg-n27c&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Footer&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not the most interesting table, yeah I know. HTML tables, not really my thing. But this is what our end result should look like, structurally.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Basic Structure &lt;/h4&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These few lines make up a basic web page. You will see that this is quite similar to what we&#39;re doing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;And this is how a basic blogger template looks like.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot; ?&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;html b:version=&#39;2&#39; class=&#39;v2&#39; expr:dir=&#39;data:blog.languageDirection&#39; xmlns=&#39;http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml&#39; xmlns:b=&#39;http://www.google.com/2005/gml/b&#39; xmlns:data=&#39;http://www.google.com/2005/gml/data&#39; xmlns:expr=&#39;http://www.google.com/2005/gml/expr&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;data:blog.pageTitle/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;b:skin&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[ /* CSS here */ ]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/b:skin&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Blog elements here --&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pretty neat, isn&#39;t it? Now, the elements of a blogger blog.  Blogger is built upon XHTML, and uses the same for retrieving and displaying data from the database. A basic block of a blogger template is called a template. So all of these are sections.    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#999;} .tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#999;color:#444;background-color:#F7FDFA;} .tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#999;color:#fff;background-color:#26ADE4;} .tg .tg-vpsr{font-size:26px;text-align:center} .tg .tg-szh5{font-size:26px} .tg .tg-n27c{font-size:26px;background-color:#bbdaff;color:#343434;text-align:center} &lt;/style&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;tg&quot;&gt;  &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;    &lt;th class=&quot;tg-vpsr&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Header&lt;/th&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;tg-szh5&quot;&gt;Blog Posts                        &lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;tg-szh5&quot;&gt;Sidebar&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;    &lt;td class=&quot;tg-n27c&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Footer&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;And you have to define each &lt;i&gt;section&lt;/i&gt; before you add &#39;&lt;i&gt;widgets&lt;/i&gt;&#39; to them. A basic section block looks like this.    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;b:section id=&#39; &#39; class=&#39; &#39; maxwidgets=&#39; &#39; showaddelement=&#39; &#39;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/b:section&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;where &lt;i&gt;id&lt;/i&gt; is any unique identifier (for CSS and JS later) and &lt;i&gt;class&lt;/i&gt; value is used to tell blogger where do we plan to place this section. &lt;i&gt;Maxelements&lt;/i&gt; is the maximum number of &#39;widgets&#39; we can add to this section. Generally, it is useful to limit the number of widgets in header and footer to one. &lt;i&gt;Showaddelement &lt;/i&gt;is that &#39;Add gadget&#39; link you see in the layout window. It takes boolean value &#39;true&#39; or &#39;false&#39;.    Now there are &#39;&lt;i&gt;widgets&lt;/i&gt;&#39; that go into these sections. Every separate component that you see on your blog is a widget. The &#39;blog posts&#39; is one widget, &#39;blog archive&#39; is another, and so on. These widgets can be directly added from the graphical layout tab in the control panel of your blog, but it doesn&#39;t hurt to know how to add them manually, does it?    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;b:widget id=&quot;HTML2&quot; locked=&quot;false&quot; title=&quot;Some Title&quot; type=&quot;HTML&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;Similarly here,  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;id&lt;/b&gt; - is just an unique ID&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;locked&lt;/b&gt; - can the widget be moved around, in the layout tab? (yes or no)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;title&lt;/b&gt; - The title that will be displayed on top of the widget&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;type&lt;/b&gt; - One of the many basic types that blogger supports (html, blog, feed, header etc)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&amp;nbsp;For example, your &#39;blog posts&#39; widget will be something like this    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;b:widget id=&#39;blog1&#39; locked=&#39;true&#39; title=&#39;&#39; type=&#39;Blog&#39; /&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;That&#39;s it. Add it to the template and blogger will fill it with auto-generated code you need not care about.    This was all for the basics. Let&#39;s start with some code now. I am using &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; to save myself from writing unnecessary CSS. First thing you do here is enclose the entire body in either &lt;i&gt;container&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;container-fluid&lt;/i&gt; div.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;container&lt;/b&gt; - for fixed width layout&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;container-fluid&lt;/b&gt; - for dynamic body width&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;I personally prefer fixed. This is the code so far. I added container class to the &amp;lt;b:skin&amp;gt; which we can (and will) customize later.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot; ?&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;html b:version=&#39;2&#39; class=&#39;v2&#39; expr:dir=&#39;data:blog.languageDirection&#39; xmlns=&#39;http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml&#39; xmlns:b=&#39;http://www.google.com/2005/gml/b&#39; xmlns:data=&#39;http://www.google.com/2005/gml/data&#39; xmlns:expr=&#39;http://www.google.com/2005/gml/expr&#39;&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;data:blog.pageTitle/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;b:skin&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[ .container { }&amp;nbsp; ]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/b:skin&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&#39;container&#39;&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Now add the divs for header, post area, right sidebar and footer and corresponding CSS classes. Code trimmed for brivity.    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;data:blog.pageTitle/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;link href=&#39;https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.4/css/bootstrap.min.css&#39; rel=&#39;stylesheet&#39;/&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;b:skin&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[ &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;#container {&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; max-width: 960px;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; margin: 0 auto; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;} &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;#main-wrapper {&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; width: 710px;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; float: left; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;#sidebar-wrapper {&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; width: 250px;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; float: right;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;#footer-widgets {&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; padding: 0px 0px 5px 0px;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/b:skin&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&#39;container&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;!-- Header --&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;b:section class=&#39;header&#39; id=&#39;header&#39; maxwidgets=&#39;1&#39; showaddelement=&#39;yes&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;b:widget id=&#39;Header1&#39; locked=&#39;true&#39; title=&#39;Blog title&#39; type=&#39;Header&#39; /&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/b:section&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&#39;main-wrapper&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;!-- Blog posts area --&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;b:section class=&#39;main&#39; id=&#39;main&#39; maxwidgets=&#39;&#39; showaddelements=&#39;yes&#39; /&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;b:widget id=&#39;Blog1&#39; locked=&#39;false&#39; title=&#39;Blog Posts&#39; type=&#39;Blog&#39; /&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/b:section&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&#39;sidebar-wrapper&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;!-- Right sidebar --&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;b:section class=&#39;sidebar&#39; id=&#39;sidebar&#39; maxwidgets=&#39;&#39; showaddelements=&#39;yes&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;!-- Widgets can be added from layout page --&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/b:section&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;div id=&#39;footer-widgets&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;!-- Footer --&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;b:section class=&#39;footer&#39; id=&#39;footer&#39; maxwidgets=&#39;&#39; showaddelements=&#39;yes&#39;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;lt;b:widget id=&#39;Attribution1&#39; locked=&#39;false&#39; title=&#39;&#39; type=&#39;Attribution&#39; /&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/b:section&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt; &lt;/pre&gt;The above code should look like this on any blogger blog.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-mhjlclELQ1g/VXG8gN1UNgI/AAAAAAAAH9Q/ELu1NPjCcn4/s1600/Screenshot%2B-%2BFriday%2B05%2BJune%2B2015%2B-%2B07%253A45%253A18%2B%2BIST.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;261&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-mhjlclELQ1g/VXG8gN1UNgI/AAAAAAAAH9Q/ELu1NPjCcn4/s400/Screenshot%2B-%2BFriday%2B05%2BJune%2B2015%2B-%2B07%253A45%253A18%2B%2BIST.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;The mobile site, I must say, would look horrible. Extra efforts are needed to make the template responsive. Since we already have Bootstrap, that is not a big deal either. I must conclude this post now, and for mobile friendly site, I may write an article soon.    Also, there is no SEO in this template. You must add relevant &lt;i&gt;&amp;lt;meta&amp;gt;&lt;/i&gt; tags to make your blog more search engine friendly. You can always override CSS rules of bootstrap by writing your own in the &lt;i&gt;&amp;lt;b:skin&amp;gt;&lt;/i&gt; section.    Thank you for reading! </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>TechMax Publications - Plagiarism Check</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/techmax-publications-plagiarism-check.html"/>
   <updated>2015-06-13T13:24:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/techmax-publications-plagiarism-check</id>
   <content type="html">I study for my finals from various sources, the Internet, class notes and some reference books. This time though, I had this &lt;a href=&quot;http://erp.techmaxbooks.com/PublisherBookList/BookDetails.aspx?kayMkNnwpPya//Mnxx+KW2tpeIIYHMDUJ1VBQqCfT3k=&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Computer Graphics, by Sanjesh Pawale, Techmax Publications&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The books from this publishing house are everything what a Mumbai University guy needs to study for exam. Well, not exactly, but that&#39;s how most see this book as.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So when I was reading it, I noticed that much of what I read in the book was something I already read someplace else. A quick browser history lookup revealed that the stuff were taken from Wikipedia. Wait, let me rephrase it, &lt;i&gt;the stuff were copied and pasted from Wikipedia&lt;/i&gt;, including the text, images and caption.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For your information, the content of Wikipedia is licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;creative commons attribution share-alike 3.0&lt;/a&gt;. The license states that &lt;i&gt;the usage is unrestricted. even for commercial use as long as appropriate credits are given and indications of modifications are made. Moreover, the content, modified or original, must be distributed under the same license&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;332&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-o2NrEFeVaTk/VXvSyB6nXsI/AAAAAAAAH9w/ecQdEWU-Q2A/s400/Screenshot%2B-%2BSaturday%2B13%2BJune%2B2015%2B-%2B12%253A19%253A21%2B%2BIST.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;But there&#39;s a bummer. The content copied by Techmax shows no attribution, no credits to Wikipedia or it&#39;s authors, and the worst, they have copyrighted the book under their name and it&#39;s totally restricted.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-LqaJb18LxKc/VXvW0H6f4AI/AAAAAAAAH98/gfdg6JMMOzY/s1600/20150613_122354.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-LqaJb18LxKc/VXvW0H6f4AI/AAAAAAAAH98/gfdg6JMMOzY/s400/20150613_122354.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Here is a piece of text from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Copyrights&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Copyrights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;To re-distribute text on Wikipedia in any form, provide credit to the authors either by including a) a hyperlink (where possible) or URL  to the page or pages you are re-using, b) a hyperlink (where possible)  or URL to an alternative, stable online copy which is freely accessible,  which conforms with the license, and which provides credit to the  authors in a manner equivalent to the credit given on this website, or  c) a list of all authors. (Any list of authors may be filtered to  exclude very small or irrelevant contributions.)&lt;/blockquote&gt;So it is mandatory for TechMax to provide a backlink to the webpage they are lifting the content from. At least a bibliography at the end of the book. The second part to this is copyleft/share-alike policy. To quote,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;If you make modifications or additions to the page you re-use, you must  license them under the Creative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License  3.0 or later. &lt;/blockquote&gt;Hence, Techmax is also violating this by copyrighting the content under their own restricting license. They should consider revising their license.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And finally, as far as the students are concerned, why not just take a little more effort and learn from the web instead of a printed version of the web.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Edit&lt;/b&gt;. A little proof of what I am talking about. The content in the image in copyrighted by *cough* Techmax *cough* and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halftone&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-tAoGrWHiLtw/VXvfcCbT5sI/AAAAAAAAH-M/-cAT2Hu4gtg/s1600/20150613_120230.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;640&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-tAoGrWHiLtw/VXvfcCbT5sI/AAAAAAAAH-M/-cAT2Hu4gtg/s640/20150613_120230.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://erp.techmaxbooks.com/PublisherBookList/BookDetails.aspx?kayMkNnwpPya//Mnxx+KW2tpeIIYHMDUJ1VBQqCfT3k=&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Techmax&lt;/a&gt;, page8-23&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-VGkbwax-UrE/VXvfy9faRRI/AAAAAAAAH-U/2eAmhQW4cHw/s1600/Screenshot%2B-%2BSaturday%2B13%2BJune%2B2015%2B-%2B12%253A00%253A48%2B%2BIST.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;385&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-VGkbwax-UrE/VXvfy9faRRI/AAAAAAAAH-U/2eAmhQW4cHw/s640/Screenshot%2B-%2BSaturday%2B13%2BJune%2B2015%2B-%2B12%253A00%253A48%2B%2BIST.png&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halftone&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;As I said, this is just an instance. If anybody is interested, just send me a mail. I would be more than happy to provide you with more proof. Cheers!</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Day Of Struggle With Python IDEs</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/a-day-of-struggle-with-python-ides.html"/>
   <updated>2015-06-04T15:17:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/a-day-of-struggle-with-python-ides</id>
   <content type="html">Yesterday, I gave up on doing my next web application project with QT. I knew C++ was never meant to be a language of the web, but I really had some hopes with QT. It actually is good, and apparently it would have ran faster than any other platform or language for the web. The problem is, it is a lot time consuming to develop anything in it, especially web apps. I really don&#39;t have all that time. So I decided to do it in Python or Ruby. After reading some articles, it became clear, they are not much different, where python is a more general programming language, ruby is more towards the web, with it&#39;s rails framework.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I choose Python, just because I know how to write code in python, beforehand. It was time to go shopping for some good frameworks to develop this thing. No doubt, finally I had to decide between &lt;a href=&quot;https://wakatime.com/django-vs-flask-worksheet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Django and Flask&lt;/a&gt;. I choose flask. It was damn too simple, or at least it seemed like that. I tried the simple hello.py script which displays &lt;i&gt;&quot;hello world&quot;&lt;/i&gt; on the localhost port 5000.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I tried that in emacs, but immediately felt the need for an IDE in this foreign land. I looked in my &#39;Downloads&#39; folder, and luckily there was Aptana Studio 3 still sitting there. I used to have it installed when I was into PHP last year. Since then, it got removed and thrown into a corner. I installed it. I really loved Aptana back then, for it&#39;s usability. But now, it started to act like a stubborn child, refusing to detect Flask. I googled and googled, but alas, no way. Many people seemed to be having the same problem, and the only solution I saw didn&#39;t work.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Seeing no way, I uninstalled Aptana, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/81584/what-ide-to-use-for-python&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;googled for other good IDEs&lt;/a&gt;. PyCharm was what most were recommending. I decided to give it a try. Turned out, it was a memory hogger. Both my CPUs were doing a constant 100% and other windows turned sluggish too. About half a tonne of RAM was what it was utilizing, with a single .py file open with 4 lines of text in it. No way, again. Removed it, and went to eat some food. Damn.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was not ready to go to the sluggish Eclipse again, nor Netbeans for the same reason. Finally I settled for Komodo Edit, free lite version of the commercial Komodo IDE. It lacks many things that you will ask for in an IDE, and it is a little better than using bare emacs or vim. Still, for now, I am using it. Configured it to execute python script right inside the window following this tutorial, &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/21686395/how-to-run-the-first-python-program-in-komodo-edit-8-5&quot;&gt;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/21686395/how-to-run-the-first-python-program-in-komodo-edit-8-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Life&#39;s good, but just hoping to learn flask for my next project as fast as I can.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Grammar Nazi</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/grammar-nazi.html"/>
   <updated>2015-06-03T13:26:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/06/grammar-nazi</id>
   <content type="html">Let&#39;s start with a story. I go for workout in a nearby gymnasium. A few days back, I remember, it was a hot day, and we were all sweating, in spite of the air conditioner running continuously. One of my mates then, asked the gym trainer to increase the cooling of the AC. The trainer replied with &quot;It is already on 18&quot;. He then asked the trainer to make it 21 or 24 so that the cooling might increase. Hearing this, we all had a burst of laugh, since the guy thought increasing the number on the display would increase the cooling.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now think about it this way. Many of you reading this might have an air conditioner at home, so you might know what this number on the display of the indoor unit means. It means degree Celsius, a unit of temperature. Even if you don&#39;t have an air conditioner, like me, you might have had the privilege of learning it in school or someplace else, that &lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;°&lt;i&gt;C &lt;/i&gt;means degree Celsius. Now what if somebody never got a chance to know this? Neither was he privileged enough to have a closer look at an air conditioner at home or workplace, nor did he get a chance to study science. Would you make fun of him, for his ignorance? Or would you give him a word or two about his lack of knowledge and make him understand stuff? I am sure you would&#39;ve taught him.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;Now is the time, when people take pride in correcting other people&#39;s grammar when on the Internet. It is in vogue. Insulting somebody just because he or she speaks in broken English is cool. It immediately makes you look like a badass. It gives people an idea about your intellectual prowess. It clearly states that you had the privilege to attend a good English medium school and had the chance to read nice books.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;Think about someone who didn&#39;t get to attend a good school because of his or her personal problems. They never got to read good novels. From all the schooling they got, they are probably trying their best to speak good English. Yes, I agree some didn&#39;t take the efforts, but there are those who actually never got a chance. Life is hard. Not everyone is born privileged. You, me have no idea what the fuck people have been through. So before judging and making fun of people in public for their language, just to get that two second of fame of yours destroying somebody, remember, you can actually correct him or her politely and earn yourself a friend who looks up to you. Isn&#39;t that better?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;Speaking with proper grammar is good. Without it is fine too. Language was meant to be a way to convey thoughts and emotions. Let&#39;s keep it that way. If you are understanding what a person is saying, even with broken grammar, why not pay more attention to what he or she says and less on being an arsehole. I am sure you&#39;ll have more friends that way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;st&quot;&gt;Thank you for reading.&lt;/span&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Wall of shame - Salman Khan&#39;s verdict</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/05/wall-of-shame-salman-khans-verdict.html"/>
   <updated>2015-05-07T15:32:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/05/wall-of-shame-salman-khans-verdict</id>
   <content type="html">Salman Khan was awarded with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-32603596&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5 year jail term&lt;/a&gt; yesterday, on account of the 2002 hit and run case where he ran over 5 homeless people sleeping on the footpath, out of which, one died.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now, the law will do it&#39;s job, justice will look at who&#39;s guilty and who&#39;s not, and there is nothing for a commoner like me, to add anything into it. But then, some people really don&#39;t understand these things. Here are some of the ridiculous things I read on the Internet lately, which I felt were a bit funny and low on intelligence, except that they actually were.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name=&#39;more&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I really lost words when I read this. She maybe be rich, and even very beautiful, but she&#39;s definitely not educated.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;It&#39;s like penalising a train driver because someone decided to cross the tracks and got killed in the bargain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/salmankhancase?src=hash&quot;&gt;#salmankhancase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;— Farah Khan (@FarahKhanAli) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FarahKhanAli/status/595861607223205889&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;No one should be sleeping on the road or footpath. It is dangerous to do that just like it is dangerous to cross tracks.&lt;/div&gt;— Farah Khan (@FarahKhanAli) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FarahKhanAli/status/595863980008144896&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Then maybe she got a blow to her head and came back to her senses. Or maybe not!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;My ppl not sleeping on the road tweet is meant to mock the govt not d poor ppl Bec every govt is responsible to provide housing to its ppl&lt;/div&gt;— Farah Khan (@FarahKhanAli) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FarahKhanAli/status/595886953876234240&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;For d record I never meant to mock d poor and if any of u read my tweets carefully I have not mocked the homeless.I blamed the govt not them&lt;/div&gt;— Farah Khan (@FarahKhanAli) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FarahKhanAli/status/596149921431965697&quot;&gt;May 7, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And then there was this guy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Suicide is crime so is sleeping on footpath..80% homeles film ppl strugld achievd stardom but never slept on footpath &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BeingSalmanKhan&quot;&gt;@BeingSalmanKhan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;— abhijeet  (@abhijeetsinger) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abhijeetsinger/status/595868019429019649&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Why not just call the case a suicide and let the convict free?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Come out fraternity, support &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BeingSalmanKhan&quot;&gt;@BeingSalmanKhan&lt;/a&gt; boldly not hypocriticly Roads footpath r not meant 4 sleeping, not driver&#39;s or alcohol&#39;s fault&lt;/div&gt;— abhijeet  (@abhijeetsinger) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abhijeetsinger/status/595860362194354176&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;And then the justification for DUI, driving under influence came in.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Etycdgrh5yQ/VUs222YAmjI/AAAAAAAAH74/0KDctx9JnVM/s1600/CEUK9F7VIAIkxco.jpg%3Alarge.jpeg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Etycdgrh5yQ/VUs222YAmjI/AAAAAAAAH74/0KDctx9JnVM/s1600/CEUK9F7VIAIkxco.jpg%3Alarge.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;115&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;This is real mature.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Mumbai ke road Aur footpath pe sone ka shauk hai ?? Y not at your village no vehicles to kill u.. Support &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BeingSalmanKhan&quot;&gt;@BeingSalmanKhan&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sonakshisinha&quot;&gt;@sonakshisinha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;— abhijeet  (@abhijeetsinger) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abhijeetsinger/status/595862521329766400&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Forgetting they are as much Mumbaikars, as you are.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;My tweets r bitter bt true..knowing that footpaths r risky they&#39;re still sleeping..Who&#39;s fault it&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BeingSalmanKhan&quot;&gt;@BeingSalmanKhan&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/OV6UDZgflN&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/OV6UDZgflN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;— abhijeet  (@abhijeetsinger) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abhijeetsinger/status/596149289329369088&quot;&gt;May 7, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Then, looking forward to some community servicing and preaching to wash off what he said, but yes, still standing by it. After all, it is a celeb&#39;s ego.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;I support my friend but i would never support such insensitive and negative talk. Please dont tag me in ur tweets &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abhijeetsinger&quot;&gt;@abhijeetsinger&lt;/a&gt; sir.&lt;/div&gt;— Sonakshi Sinha (@sonakshisinha) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sonakshisinha/status/595927607859744768&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;When famous personalities don&#39;t support you. It hurts right? After all, they are the only ones you consider &#39;humans&#39;. Rest are dogs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Planning to drive a car over &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abhijeetsinger&quot;&gt;@abhijeetsinger&lt;/a&gt; .His fault if he dies. After all he got in the way. Gonna sue him later for injuring my car.&lt;/div&gt;— $ir $ri $ri Magal (@jhunjhunwala) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jhunjhunwala/status/595901940279554048&quot;&gt;May 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;This fight is still on, and will continue for a day or two. If you are one of those in bollywood who get very little to no attention from media these days, now&#39;s the time to shine. Post something shitty and get interviewed. For free.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Debian 8 Jessie is here</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/05/debian-8-jessie-is-here.html"/>
   <updated>2015-05-01T21:13:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/05/debian-8-jessie-is-here</id>
   <content type="html">The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.debian.org/releases/stable/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;next major stable release&lt;/a&gt; of the Debian lineup, the 8th one, codename Jessie was launched on 25th of april, last month. And like every Debian release, this one was packed with an awfully large package repo, meaning more free stuff to choose from, one of the fundamental reason I use Debian.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The total package base, with this release, is over 43,000, which is a lot. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.debian.org/News/2015/20150426&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;key features added&lt;/a&gt; to this release, make it one of the best Linux distros till date, imo. Not to mention, rock solid.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;All the major desktop environments like GNOME, KDE, XFCE, LXDE are supported (No Unity, sad ;), just select the preferred one during installation and it will download it for you. Alternatively, some iso are marked which desktop environment it ships, and if not specified explicitly, assume GNOME3.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If you are already on Debian 7, to get Jessie, fully update the system:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;sudo apt-get upgrade&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;sudo apt-get dist-upgrade.&lt;/pre&gt;Then just head to /etc/apt/sources.list and replace every occurrence of &lt;i&gt;wheezy&lt;/i&gt; with &lt;i&gt;jessie&lt;/i&gt; and then again:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;sudo apt-get upgrade&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;That would be it. I noticed that Jessie is super fast, and I intentionally did a minimal install. The bootup and shutdown speeds are very impressive. Here is an amature video of me filming the shutdown time, LOL.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EpOLUyRvkU8&quot; width=&quot;560&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A note, if you go to the downloads page, there are multiple DVDs, like for example, the amd64 complete comes in around 10 DVDs, but you only need the first one. It contains all the installation stuff and most of the packages you&#39;ll ever use, including the desktop environments.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Downloads page: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.debian.org/CD/&quot;&gt;https://www.debian.org/CD/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A tip, you can add the DVD contents to your hard drive and set up an offline repository. Mount the contents of the DVD or copy it to a local folder.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;# in case of mounting the iso&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;mount -t iso9660 -o loop /home/abhishek/Debian/debian-8.0.0-amd64-DVD-1.iso /mount_point&lt;/pre&gt;Or just plain copy iso contents into the folder. Then add the following line on top of the /etc/apt/sources.list&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;deb file:///mount_point/ jessie main contrib&lt;/pre&gt;so that it will check for a local copy of the package first for offline package installation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That was it for this promotional article [ ;) ] on Debian 8. Hope you like the new release and use it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thank you developers.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>I feel so powerless in my own country</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/04/i-feel-so-powerless-in-my-own-country.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-19T21:44:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/04/i-feel-so-powerless-in-my-own-country</id>
   <content type="html">I am not feeling very good writing on such a topic, but yes, I have really convinced myself, if I am not rich, I am nothing in this country.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is a daily sight for me, how being rich makes all the difference there is, here. If something is bothering me, I don&#39;t go complaining about it, but instead, I wait for the same thing to bother some politician or hotshot, so that he will complain and get it fixed, because even if I do complain, no one is going to hear me anyway.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is funny how thousands of people get checked at the airport everyday and no one bats an eye but when a famous celebrity goes through the same, our media loses its mind, criticizing the airport officials for doing their duty. How wealthy people demand changes and get them, and the others have to just adjust to it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I always wonder, how politicians earn that much. I mean, they have fixed salaries when they are in power, and otherwise, they have to make a living doing something else. Instead, you&#39;ll find that every politician here has multiple houses in posh areas, farm houses, run their own colleges. Where does this lot of money come from? How come a guy, who has not worked a single hour, doesn&#39;t have a job nor any apparent legit business, roams around in a Jaguar, is respected by authority, is called upon as chief guest in functions and his orders are given more importance than the orders of law.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I live in a country where the people from military, police and the farmers are amongst the lowest earning people. They are overlooked most of the times, hardly make a living to keep their families fulfilled. On the other hand, we have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/pictures/emdm45hmgh/1-mahendra-singh-dhoni/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cricketers making billions of rupees&lt;/a&gt;, celebrities that are treated like deities and politicians and business people who get to take decisions on behalf of the entire nation. I have nothing against people who earn with their own efforts, but when some people keep all the money for themselves, it is the common people who suffer. And as money is synonymous to power and authority here in India, most of the people are robbed off their basic rights. Maybe I don&#39;t, but the people who sacrifice their lives for the nation deserve a better standard of living. When you see the kids of farmers not going to school because he can&#39;t even afford to feed them, let alone sending them to school, a part of you dies within. The guy who feeds the nation is unable to feed his own family, and the people who have put on the false mask of saving the culture and religion of this country, eat at international food joints and roam around in imported cars. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here, people don&#39;t help others to rise. Instead, when one is going down, he is pushed even harder. When people here find a source of income, they exploit it to the fullest, gathering as much as they can, until they can. See cricket for example. There is awful lot of money here. All other sports are ignored, only cricket. They give the excuse that cricket is a religion here, but the truth is, money is the religion here. Greed is, maybe, a human instinct. Here, people are not greedy, they are impaired by their brain, poor by their thoughts, disabled in terms of sensitivity. Check out the condition of sports that don&#39;t make money here. It is left to rot.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;People in India are highly religious. They stand by their religion and people no matter what. The common people at least. This fact is well exploited by the politicians these days. Drag any argument into this dirt and hurt the sentiments of the weak hearted. Then follows the riots and jams, the damaging to the public property and what not. All this, just so that some people can get into the good books of the majority of the people who follow a religion and hope they help those some people to win elections. Pretty foolish, you might say. No, it really works. Welcome to India.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You visit a temple. First thing you notice is two separate queues, one for the commoners and the other for the VIPs. The commoners line can get really long at occasions, sometimes 4-5 hours in queue. The VIP line hardly reaches any long, most of the times 10 minutes tops. Now some &lt;i&gt;wise &lt;/i&gt;folks argue that at the end both get to see the same God. Yeah, good luck convincing yourself that. This is just an example of what happens everyday, at everyplace in the country.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Do you know what bullies look like in India? No, they are not the fat ugly huge guys, but rather they are the ones who are friends with local politicians, who can get a gang standing by them on a mere call, who will beat you up along with half dozen of his friends even if you were right, and then even if you die, proving that he was the culprit in India will probably take the next 20 years in court who by then will have settled in some damn foreign country where our jurisdiction doesn&#39;t apply. This is what will happen. &lt;a href=&quot;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Warren-Anderson-CEO-of-Union-Carbide-during-the-1984-Bhopal-gas-tragedy-dies/articleshow/44992106.cms&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;This is what has been happening&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Do you see the pattern. You can get off with any crime here in India. If you are a celebrity, you can walk in and out of the jail during your term, just like you do in a park, with obvious BS excuses. You can do whatever the hell you want to in this country, provided that you are rich.&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;I am not. Now you know why I feel so powerless in my own country.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Net Neutrality</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/04/net-neutrality.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-13T22:50:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/04/net-neutrality</id>
   <content type="html">Do you know, here in India, at most of the public places like temples, we have two separate queues. One for the ordinary folks, and the other one for the rich folks. Sometimes the rich folks are charged, sometimes they are just judged from the car they get down from and are treated likewise. On the other hand, the ordinary people are treated like cattles, pulled and pushed by the authority, because we are not really benefiting them much.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the reason I would almost always choose Internet over any other public institution, at least in India. I know that whatever my social status be, on the Internet, I am equal. I have just as much right to put forth by thoughts as any rich businessman or a politician. I know that I have got people behind me who would not tolerate anyone who curtails my rights on the Internet. Yes, Internet is my home, and I am Internet&#39;s child.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But like always, there are people who cannot stand that the ordinary are getting this extra power. They want to bring all of this under control. They want to turn the Internet into their own playground where they will control the lines as in our temples, giving early and quick access to the one who pays extra and slow to the one who does not. They want to make sure only the ones who can pay get heard, and all the others are suppressed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Net Neutrality&lt;/h3&gt;You are out with your family, on a nice sunday picnic when on a toll booth, you are told that your Maruti car is no longer allowed on this flyover because Hyundai has paid the construction company to only allow their cars through the shortcut. What would be your reaction?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;320&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-lAAz-YJyr2k/VSt8xLCNxNI/AAAAAAAAH7g/wHM831EryY8/s1600/Black-Girl-Wat.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot; width=&quot;306&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;This, precisely! &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot; style=&quot;clear: both; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&lt;/a&gt; (&#39;Inventor&#39; or the world wide web, or more technically, original implementer of the HTTP protocol) defines &#39;Net Neutrality&#39; as the principle that each packet of data should be treated equally, and no discrimination should be made based on economic motivations.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The exact opposite is what some telecom companies in India are trying to do. It started with Airtel. All of a sudden, it struck Airtel that if websites and applications can make revenue by creating services like messaging (like Whatsapp and Facebook) and calling (like Skype and Viber) which in turn decrease the usage of Airtel&#39;s own services of SMS and calling, it is their right to start charging these Internet services separately. They even got out with their VOIP pack that a customer had to subscribe in addition to the existing &#39;base&#39; data pack, to use this service. &lt;a href=&quot;http://in.reuters.com/article/2014/12/29/bharti-airtel-rates-idINKBN0K70A920141229&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eventually it was dropped&lt;/a&gt; on account of the resistance.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now this time, telecom companies have convinced &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trai.gov.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TRAI&lt;/a&gt; that they must be entitled with the authority to intercept the traffic, to decide what websites to let users access, and what not, and if yes, then at what speed. Ridiculous, right? Charging more for extra speed can be justified, but why on earth are those innocent data packets discriminated. TRAI has even released a consultation paper &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trai.gov.in/Content/ConDis/10743_0.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;asking 20 questions here&lt;/a&gt;. If you take a look, you would immediately see that the paper is made extra complicated to not make sense to you, yes you, the customer. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://isocpp.org/std/the-standard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;C++ standard&lt;/a&gt; looks simpler. LOL.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;So what does it change for you, for me?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;i&gt;As a customer&lt;/i&gt;, it will change almost everything for us that has any connection with the Internet. Firstly, we will have to pay for the usual data plan we currently do. So far so good. Now, you can&#39;t use any messenger services from this pack, so no Whatsapp, Facebook, WeChat and all. Similarly, no Internet calling services would work, like Skype and Viber. Well, they would work if you pay an extra Rs100 or so a month for the &#39;Special-messenger-pack&#39; and the &#39;Special-VOIP-pack&#39;. Now who the heck are these telecom companies to tell me how and what sites and services should I use.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Plus, it also gives the companies the power to control the speed of your connection on particular sites. For example, maybe Flipkart.com will load up instantly, but Amazon.in would take forever to load up just because Flipkart is affiliated with your service provider, and you are forced to buy from Flipkart. Disgusting, right?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So, if you don&#39;t want to pay Rs250 for data, Rs50 for Whatsapp, Rs70 for Facebook and Rs80 for Youtube seperately, then you should instantly head to&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savetheinternet.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.savetheinternet.in/ &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;and send an email to TRAI, which can be done with 2 clicks, yes literally.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;As a publisher&lt;/i&gt;, you might own a startup or maybe a modest blog like the one you are reading this article on. Now, large sites and enterprises with deep pockets can just call up these telecom companies and be like &quot;Make my site free on your network, I&#39;ll pay you the incentive.&quot; This will make all the traffic go on that particular site or use that particular service and not yours, which was equally good, or maybe better.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Internet is the only place guys, where everyone is still equal. We need to keep it this way, otherwise, we would be helpless. We know exactly how strong our law is, and how well behaved our politicians are. We know exactly how seriously we are taken by the mainstream media and the police. We, Indians, are like puppets for the rich filthy and greedy companies that rule here. And now, they are trying to close the only open source of information for us. Don&#39;t let that happen.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A humble request to all my fellow netizens. Log on to the site and send an email to TRAI. Educate your fellow netizens. Together we can stop this.&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savetheinternet.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.savetheinternet.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;For further reading, here is a short list.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.netneutrality.in/&quot;&gt;http://www.netneutrality.in/&lt;/a&gt; - More information and compilation of articles.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/netneutralityin&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/netneutralityin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/neutrality_in&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/neutrality_in&lt;/a&gt; - Social handles to follow for latest updates.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Awesome video by All India Bakchod to put it simply - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mfY1NKrzqi0&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mfY1NKrzqi0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/india/comments/31lyxx/table_of_companies_which_support_net_neutrality/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;List of violators and supporters of net neutrality,&lt;/a&gt; so the next time you have to choose between them, you know whose side to take and whose product to use.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@chupchap/india-s-net-neutrality-debate-explained-in-memes-3a8f6febaccf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Post on Medium by NT Balanarayan&lt;/a&gt; explaining the intensity of this situation with memes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trai.gov.in/WriteReaddata/ConsultationPaper/Document/OTT-CP-27032015.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TRAI Consultation paper&lt;/a&gt; hot-link (PDF)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.change.org/p/telecom-regulatory-authority-of-india-call-to-protect-net-neutrality-in-india-and-block-airtel-other-telecoms-from-who-are-trying-to-break-it-for-personal-gains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Petition on Change.org&lt;/a&gt; - You should help here as well. The more you help, the better our chances.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What programming isn&#39;t</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/04/what-programming-isnt.html"/>
   <updated>2015-04-10T20:12:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/04/what-programming-isnt</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;There were days when I used to search the web for &#39;&lt;i&gt;best programming languages&lt;/i&gt;&#39; and &#39;&lt;i&gt;most popular programming languages&lt;/i&gt;&#39; in my free time. I was not able to decide myself what language to learn and invest my time upon, such that it would pay me back everything I put into it. This was really a hard task, given the fact that I have interest in a wide range of stuff related to computers, from algorithms to designing beautiful forms with CSS.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Given that I had no guidance from the people around me, since I had no one in my family from the technical field, and the college professors were not of much help either. Now that justifies my amateur-ish googling habits.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Leaving that aside, I have lately been asked a lot of times by my fellow mates, what is the &#39;&lt;i&gt;best language&lt;/i&gt;&#39; to start with and what are the current &#39;&lt;i&gt;hot languages&lt;/i&gt;&#39; in the market. To start with, there is no language that is &#39;best&#39; in every sense. If there was, why would anyone bother creating additional languages in the first place, right? Languages are written and implemented with certain goals in mind, which it should satisfies better than what was present before creating that language, that&#39;s the whole point about it. So stop searching for the best language and start looking for your own needs.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Secondly, I don&#39;t think anybody should care about the &#39;hot languages&#39; in the market, except for the tech magazines&#39; journalists. Why? Because if you haven&#39;t heard of it yet, then you probably don&#39;t actually need it yet. It is much better to know a single language as a whole, than to learn 5 languages just for the sake of them being &#39;hot&#39;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;If you are new to programming, then most probably you are taught programming using some or the other language (most probably C++ or Python). What most fail to teach is that programming is not equal to learning a language. Programming is the mindset that you develop when you are solving problem for a wide range of sub-problems by writing a common solution to all. Most of the times it means looking for a pattern in the chaos of that problem. You don&#39;t need to know a language for finding this pattern, do you? You have to realize this thing at the earliest.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Programming language that you choose is the tool you choose for the task you have in hand. Now, depending upon the task, some tool might be better than the others, and help you in doing the task quicker. You can think of an analogy here, like if you want to cut tree trunks, you can use saw blade or maybe even a kitchen knife. But the saw will get the job done much faster. However, any sane human won&#39;t cut vegetables using a saw. The same goes for programming languages. Different tasks demand different languages, and each has its own pros and cons. But the languages won&#39;t help a bit if you cannot figure out the problem itself in the first place.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I had start to program in C, jumped to Python because &#39;Google used it&#39;. Then I came to PHP because I read somewhere that PHP gets you a job quickly. I started with JS and Node.js later due to their growing popularity. I did a lot of mistakes when I started it all. I wish I knew it then, that instead of wasting my time on learning the syntax of languages to do the exact same thing I did with the previous language, I could have been much better off learning some interesting algorithms that would&#39;ve helped me in solving some tough hackathon problems.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;So is the knowledge of language implementations not useful? Of course, I don&#39;t mean that. A language is very useful once you know how to use it. You don&#39;t have to know everything from a language. Just enough to get the problem solved. Nothing more. For example, you might have probably heard of C++. If you have ever tried to learn C++, you might have realized that it is a really large language. Originally designed for low level embedded programming and as a &#39;C with Classes&#39;, C++ has evolved to be a language that can be used in almost every domain. The &#39;Standard Template Library&#39; is large enough for you to not miss anything in most of the cases, and even if you do, there is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boost.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;boost&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at your rescue. So do you think you most know all of the above to call yourself a C++ programmer? No. Many great programmers who use this language use just a subset of it and they are fine with it. I personally don&#39;t use the object oriented facilities of the language much, but it doesn&#39;t matter as long as it does what you want it to do. So don&#39;t aim to know an entire language unless you want to get into compiler development or it&#39;s standardization committee. Focus on the thing you are working on, and not the language you are using.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Have the enthusiasm to solve problems. Take pride in building things from the scratch, all by yourself. The love for programming comes in automatically. But most important of all, learn how to program and not how to write syntax of a particular language.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Thank you for reading.&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Engineering</title>
   <link href="http://www.nagekar.com/2015/03/engineering.html"/>
   <updated>2015-03-07T18:05:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://www.nagekar.com/2015/03/engineering</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;i&gt;Engineer&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;What comes to your mind when you hear that word? To me, the picture of a hard working individual, who is rational in his way of life, sees every aspect with the touch of technicality, given a job, he will do whatever it takes to get it done, selfless about his own personal pleasures, solving the problems of this world, one by one.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Well, at least that is what comes to my mind. The reality is far from it. We have more &lt;a href=&quot;http://dazeinfo.com/2014/10/28/1-5-million-engineering-pass-outs-india-every-year-fewer-getting-hired-trends/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;engineering colleges&lt;/a&gt; here in India than we have good hospitals. Why? Because you cannot charge Rs.400k from each patient that visits your hospital the way you can from the students that study engineering course. In the particular state that I live in, engineering colleges are a part time income source of the politicians here. See the problem in India is, everybody wants to get rich, before the other one. Now there is nothing wrong with it as long as you don&#39;t steal people from their rights.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A student, passed out from junior college, is an empty vase eager to absorb knowledge. He is excited about his life ahead, his life in a professional institute where he will be taught the essentials to work in the industry for most of his life later. He has dreams, just like everyone. He has interests, and he tries very hard to get the stream of his choice. He had been working hard since the very day he got admitted in school for this particular moment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally the moment of truth arrives. He is admitted into a good college. He even gets the stream of his choice. There is no bounds to his happiness. His life is all set to rock, in a sense. Isn&#39;t it? His parents pay their hard earned money to the college, thinking that it will benefit their child to become a better man, an &#39;educated&#39; person, a responsible citizen. Now the student&#39;s joy know no bounds. He is excited as a child is on his first visit to an amusement park. The can&#39;t sleep the day before his first day at college. Its time.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On the first day of college, he wakes up early. Gets ready and dashes his way to the college. He has 4-5 blank books in his bag, to make notes on what the professor teaches. He trips on the way multiple times due to excitement. On reaching the college, he takes the first bench in the class. &quot;I would be able to pay more attention from here&quot;, he whispers. The professor enters the classroom with a set of papers and a fat reference book. He speaks out his name, rather lifelessly, and gives a very brief intro on the topic he would be teaching that semester. The intro was rather too short.&quot;This is it? Why doesn&#39;t he speak more on it.&quot; whispers the student. He was enjoying it. But the professor must hurry, a vast syllabus is waiting to get done.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The rest of the day goes similar. Nothing out of the ordinary. Nobody wants to talk anything out of the textbook. Probably it will waste a lot of time of the professor. Days pass by, and the only thing that changes is the number of books in the student&#39;s bag. From 6 to 3 and then to one common rough book for all subjects. No, not because he was lazy to carry them all, but the pathetic quality of notes his teachers gave, he simply didn&#39;t feel like they are worth of writing in separate books.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After a few boring days with no activity, which he later realizes were the best days of the semester, the professor starts to give them assignments as homework. Not the kind of assignments where you can research and write on your own, but the &lt;i&gt;do-it-by-tomorrow-atleast-30-pages-or-get-a-C-grade &lt;/i&gt;kind of assignments. Alas, there isn&#39;t enough time to find the solutions. He gets readymade solutions from a friend who had copied it from another friend who might have got the solutions from previous year&#39;s journal of a senior, and copies all the answers into his assignment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is nothing in practicals too. Most of the time he is made to write journals so that he might submit them on time. So basically practicals are library hours where he gets to do nothing &#39;practical&#39; but copy from other&#39;s journals so that at least he can get an A grade, which eventually by the end of the semester gets him 5 additional marks, at the cost of wasting the precious practical hours where he could have maybe learnt how that particular IC works.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Days fly by quickly. Sitting for lectures where you don&#39;t understand a word of what the professor says, but still have to, for attendance. Yes, the university enforces 75% compulsory attendance but fails to enforce benchmarks for the quality of lectures the professors give. Maybe enforcing the later will automatically make the attendance, not only 75% but also 90%, of most students.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Failing to comply with the attendance policy of the college results the student not being able to attend his exams and parents getting called up to meet the professors in college. What happens when a professor comes to teach a topic he has hardly any idea of, gives the worst lecture you can possibly imagine with all bits of information flying around, and then leaves? Nothing happens. Even if you do complain about it, the replacement is as good as the old one, so most of the student don&#39;t even bother to do that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Technical festivals. Yes, the thing our colleges are famous for. Technical festival, or tech fest as we call them, are something I personally waited for the entire semester. I could imagine all the amazing stuff that would be put to display, the workshops, the seminars and the enthusiasm. When it came, it was nothing as I had in my mind. It was all guys and girls hanging out enjoying their accidental holiday. It was foolish games like laser tag, devil_maze where people were made to run through dark corridors created with black curtains and UV lights. It was nothing technical, only games-which-can-attract-most-participants-and-earn-most-ticket-fees festival.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This concludes with the semester exams, or finals. Here all we learn is the questioning pattern of the university so that we can quite accurately guess what is going to be there on the exam the next day and how am I going to fool the paper checker into believing that I know something about the topic, not much but something to earn me passing marks, after which I will spend 15 days doing nothing but hoping the next semester is better than this one.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, a student has covered 1/8th of his life in the engineering course, spending a fortune as time and money, achieving nothing, and now the only thing differs is that he knows how the rest 7/8ths of this life of his, which he highly anticipated, are going to be like. Welcome to the reality.</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
